<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The captive taken from the strong or a true relation of the gratious release of Mistrisse Deborah Huish (by the arm of the Almighty) from under the power of the Tempter, by whose firy conflicts she had been sorely vexed for about fourteen years / as it was faithfully written from her own mouth by William Allen ...</title>
            <author>Allen, William, Adjutant-general of the army in Ireland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23653</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32702</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12747339</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12747339</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93284</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23653)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93284)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1028:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The captive taken from the strong or a true relation of the gratious release of Mistrisse Deborah Huish (by the arm of the Almighty) from under the power of the Tempter, by whose firy conflicts she had been sorely vexed for about fourteen years / as it was faithfully written from her own mouth by William Allen ...</title>
                  <author>Allen, William, Adjutant-general of the army in Ireland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60], 73, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Livewel Chapman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Errata on last page.</note>
                  <note>"Abstract of the principal parts of the fore going narrative" added at end.</note>
                  <note>Pagination cropped.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conversion.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93284:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CAPTIVE <hi>Taken from the</hi> STRONG: <hi>OR,</hi> A true Relation of the gratious releaſe of Miſtriſſe <hi>Deborah Huiſh</hi> (by the Arm of the Almighty) from under the Power of the Tempter, by whoſe firy Conflicts ſhe had been ſorely vexed for about fourteen years; as it was Faithfully written from her own mouth, BY <hi>WILLIAM ALLEN,</hi> Late Adjutant-General in Ireland.</p>
            <q>
               <p>He brought me up alſo out of an horrible Pit, out of the miry Clay, and ſet my feet upon a Rock, and eſtabliſhed my goings. And he hath put a new Song in my mouth; even praiſe unto our God: Many ſhall ſee it, and fear, and ſhall trust in the Lord. <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 40.2, 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>I will never forget thy Precepts, for with them thou hast quickened me. <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 119.93.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Livewel Chapman,</hi> at the Crown in Popes-head-Alley. 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:93284:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93284:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou haſt here a true Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the various and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful dealings of the Lord with this his poor Hand-maid, now made rich in Faith, (through grace) after fourteen years exerciſe, under great horrour, and ſoul-diſmaying di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, as it was taken from her own mouth, at ſeveral times, by my ſelf, ſince the Lord by his grace inlarged her heart, cauſing her thus to ſpeak to his praiſe.</p>
            <p>The matter herein contained needs not Epiſtles of commendation, at leaſt from one ſo weak and unworthy as my ſelf, who to my grief and ſhame may ſay, have not yet attained to the leaſt part of this rich portion the Lord hath bleſs'd her ſoul with. And indeed, the whole is an Epiſtle that may be ſeen
<pb facs="tcp:93284:3"/> and read by all diſcerning Chriſtians, to have been written on her heart, by the Spirit of the living God; which I hope will more commend it to every gracious ſoul, then any thing from man can do: though when I call to mind the deep diſtreſſes of ſoul I have known her in, for ſome years paſs'd; with the gratious deliverance the Lord hath now wrought for her, agreeable to that pray'd for in <hi>Pſal. 126.4. O Turn again our captivity, O Lord, as the ſtreams in the ſouth;</hi> and fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that pretious promiſe in the <hi>5.</hi> and <hi>6. verſes</hi> of that <hi>Pſal. They that ſow in tears, ſhall reap in joy,</hi> &amp;c. I may truely ſay, I am in my own thoughts (as to the gratious ſurprizing nature of this ſpecial mercy) even as one that dreams.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> be not offended at the homely dreſſe this comes forth in, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as to often repetitions of the ſame things, with little variation, the want of Oratory, eloquence, or what elſe the wiſedom of this world calls ornament:
<pb facs="tcp:93284:3"/> this being intended chiefly for the uſe of thoſe that little mind ſuch things; it was judged, it's own natural ſimple Attire would beſt become it. Beſides, this gratious ſoul, ſince her reſcue out of Satans power, hath been under very frequent and renewed aſſaults from him, who hath ſet upon her often with the ſame temptation; and the Lord hath taught her to uſe the ſame Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons he gave her at the firſt, with great ſucceſſe, to oppoſe him at thoſe ſeveral times; which were thought neceſſary to be ſet down accordingly (as appears more particularly in the inſuing Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative) <hi>That ſo the Devil's reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe malice to diſturbe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy; and the Lord's continued faithfulneſſe to ſuccour and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> might the better be obſerved: But if it <hi>be ſubſtance thou ſeekeſt (and that will ſatisfie)</hi> I dare be bold to ſay, thou wilt here find it; yea rich treaſure (though in a poor earthen Veſſel; <hi>(which will render the praiſe of this pretious mercy more
<pb facs="tcp:93284:4"/> properly due to God, unto whom alone it belongs.)</hi> She was, when ſhe declared theſe things, much in that frame of Spirit, mentioned in <hi>1 Cor. 2.3. In weakneſſe, in fear, and in much trembling.</hi> And her ſpeech (though plain and mean) thou wilt find in ſome meaſure, anſwering that <hi>in the fourth verſe of that ſecond Chapter,</hi> viz. <hi>in the demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Spirit, and of Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of whom I may further ſay, ſhe delights not to make a fair ſhew in the fleſh, but rather to be <hi>found glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying onely in the croſs of Chriſt Jeſus, by which the world is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified unto her, and ſhe much cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified unto the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ends of Publiſhing this Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative <hi>(next to giving the glory of this mercy to the Lord, to whom alone it is due)</hi> are, firſt, <hi>to warn ſinners</hi> (eſpecially ſuch as make a mock at ſin, as in <hi>Prov. 14.9.</hi>) to take heed, how they make light of that which the Lord can (and frequently
<pb facs="tcp:93284:4"/> doth) make ſo weighty, <hi>when he binds it on the conſcience of the ſinner</hi> (as in the inſuing Narrative more at large appears; which I deſire ſuch may with <hi>fear and trembling read,</hi> and conſider well.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If God did ſo deal with this green Tree,</hi> what then <hi>may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected he will do to the drie ones?</hi> that ſo, if poſsible, ſuch might be ſtopped in their Carreer in wayes of ſin and Ruine, and cauſed to return by this poor ſouls ſad experience, who having indeed <hi>known the terrours of the Lord, doth declare them, to that end that ſhe may perſwade men.</hi> But ſecondly, and more eſpecially, <hi>that poor, drooping, diſconſolate, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged ſouls, who are, or may be ready to faint under the weight of their Iniquities, and juſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of the Lord diſcovered againſt them;</hi> who by reaſon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may be ready to ſay, as in <hi>Lament. 3.18. That their ſtrength and hope is periſhed from the Lord: and as
<pb facs="tcp:93284:5"/> in Iſai. 49.14. That the Lord hath forſaken them) might here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be ſuccored, ſupported, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged,</hi> to look towards the Lord, and <hi>the ſtrength and length of thoſe everlaſting Armes, menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in Deut. 33.27.</hi> Which may be underneath, when not diſcerned, as in this poor ſouls caſe; they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſsing and upholding <hi>(though not comforting)</hi> her, when ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected nothing but the ſtretching them out to her eternal ruine. In her four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years dangerous Voyage through ſuch a tempeſtuous troubled Sea, when all that time (as it were) neither Sun, Moon, nor Stars appeared, and her ſoul with continual Billows going over it, <hi>was ſorely afflicted, toſſed with tempeſt, and not comforted;</hi> yet he <hi>(whoſe way is in the waters, and his footſteps in the great deeps,</hi> was then with her, as in <hi>Iſai. 43.2. (when thou paſſeſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the waters, I will be with thee,</hi> &amp;c. Checking the proud
<pb facs="tcp:93284:5"/> Waves; and as is ſaid, <hi>Job 38.11.8. Hitherto ſhalt thou come, but no further; and here ſhall thy proud waves be ſtaid:)</hi> and his thoughts towards her, even all this time, <hi>as in Jer. 29.11. Thoughts of peace, and not of evil,</hi> &amp;c. and doubtleſſe ſhall alſo in due time appear to be the ſame, towards all his <hi>poor toſſed troubled ones (who for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent may walk in darkneſſe, and ſee no light, as in Iſai. 50.10.)</hi> and yet (he that hath promis'd to <hi>bring the blind by a way that they know not, as in Iſa. 42.16.</hi>) is lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them in the return, in that path <hi>mentioned, Jer. 31.9. They ſhall come with weeping, and with ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications will I lead them,</hi> &amp;c. And ſurely ſuch ſhall have cauſe in the end (<hi>with this late redeemed captive,</hi> and other pretious ones) to admire the Riches of God's infinite grace; and ſay as in <hi>Rom. 11.33. O the depth of the Riches, both of the wiſedom and knowledge of
<pb facs="tcp:93284:6"/> God! how unſearchable are his judgements, and his wayes paſt finding out!</hi> And in the mean time may hereby be helped to put ſome check to their own troubled thoughts, at leaſt ſo far as not to make them (as is too u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual) the Rule and meaſure of thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite tranſcendent thoughts and wayes of God towards them.</p>
            <p>And truely the bringing forth of ſuch <hi>a glorious work as this,</hi> out of ſuch a barren Womb <hi>of apprehended impoſſibilities (when even Faith, hopes, and hearts, of the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt failed concerning it)</hi> I cannot but think was given in at ſuch a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to <hi>raiſe our Faith and hope in the Lord,</hi> by looking upon this ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnal mercy, at a pledge and pattern of what God will yet do, not onely for <hi>poor diſconſolate ſouls in like conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but alſo for the recovery and raiſing his publicke works,</hi> ſo far gone back in theſe Nations, in this ſad declining day, as cauſeth many of <hi>Zions</hi> Friends to ſpeak ſadly and
<pb facs="tcp:93284:6"/> doubtfully of them, as they of Christ, <hi>Luke 24.20, 21, 22, 23.</hi> Who were ſad in the ſenſe of his being taken from them (as in <hi>v. 17.</hi>) and to be mourning as <hi>Mary, in John 20.13.</hi> And ſome of them are ready to faint with crying, Lord, how long? <hi>and, Help Lord, as in Pſal. 12.1.</hi> While their Enemies inſult, as <hi>in Lament. 2.16. Saying, Certainly, this is the day that we looked for.</hi> And as in <hi>Pſa. 35.20, 21. are deviſing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful matters againſt them that are quiet in the Land; and yet are ſubject to ſay, as in Jer. 50.7. They offend not,</hi> &amp;c. Yea ſome of <hi>Zions</hi> pretended lovers raiſed and lifted up (it's to be feared too highly) by her, are dealing unkindly with her; and that under higheſt pretences of real affection to the name and cauſe of God, and interest of his people (<hi>as in Iſai. 66.5. Saying, Let the Lord be glorified,</hi> &amp;c. all ſo much invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in our late <hi>publicke tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> but now almoſt all given up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:93284:7"/> the hands of thoſe that <hi>hate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, and ſcorn them;</hi> which is a ſad cauſe of lamentation; and O, that it may lie with due ſenſe upon the hearts of all <hi>Zions</hi> mourners, to ſpread before the <hi>Lord as a lamentation;</hi> and more eſpecially the cauſes of it, (ſome of which are mention'd (as I judge) <hi>Lament. 1.8, 9. Jeruſalem hath grievouſly ſinn'd,</hi> &amp;c.) That ſo we may be led thereby to the cure (which I fear we much want) as they of old, <hi>Jer. 8.6. They ſpake not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, no man repented him of his wickedneſs, ſaying, What have I done!</hi> Ah! the Lord hath yet a work to do on Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> before the rod can will be removed, as in <hi>Iſa. 10.12. Wherefore it ſhall come to paſſe, that when the Lord hath performed his whole work upon Mount</hi> Zion, <hi>and on Jeruſalem,</hi> &amp;c. And were that done, judgement would ſoon return to Righteouſneſſe, and all the upright in heart ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93284:7"/>
            <p>But alluding to the <hi>Acts 26.8. I would yet ſay, Why ſhould it be thought a thing incredible that God ſhould raiſe the dead?</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what he hath done in this <hi>late captives caſe;</hi> and what is Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied and promiſed he will do more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickely in the most needful ſeaſon, <hi>Iſai. 5.9. from the firſt to the ſixteenth, much our caſe</hi> (as thou maiest read at leaſure) and yet his cure reacheth it, mention'd in <hi>v. 17. compare alſo Iſa. 51.3. where he hath promiſed to comfort</hi> Zion <hi>with all her waſte places,</hi> &amp;c. and in <hi>v. 22, 23. Thus ſaith thy Lord, the Lord and thy God, that pleadeth the cauſe of his people; Behold, I have taken out of thine hand the cup of trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, even the dregs of the cup of my fury, thou ſhalt no more drink it again, but I will put it into the hand of them that afflict thee,</hi> &amp;c. And many other pretious words of the like import, which I ſhall not mention here, being well conſidered, doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford
<pb facs="tcp:93284:8"/> us (in this vally of <hi>Achor</hi>) a door of hope.</p>
            <p>But that I may not detain thee from this Feast of fat things, the best of which is last (according to Christs old Method) <hi>John 2.10.</hi> I ſhall haſte to a cloſe, in the words of the Pſalmist, <hi>Pſal. 107.43. Whoſo is wiſe, and will obſerve theſe things, even they ſhall underſtand the loving kindneſſe of the Lord:</hi> Which that my ſoul with thine may be taught to do, and improve accordingly; I beg thy earnest ſupplications for me at the throne of grace, who am <hi>the moſt</hi> unworthy to make mention of the name of the Lord, (or any concerns of his) yet deſire to be found in this evil day, bearing my part <hi>with his poor Mourners;</hi> having much cauſe, under the ſence of my own, and ſight of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abominations abounding in this day, calling to that duty: Yet cannot but rejoyce in this great deliverance wrought for this poor ſoul; hoping and longing for the remaining deliverances, <hi>purchaſed for (and promiſed to)</hi> whole <hi>Zion: which the Lord haſten in his time: even ſo,</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. ALLEN.</signed>
               <dateline>Sand in Devon <date>the ſecond day of the firſt Moneth, <hi>1657.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93284:8"/>
            <head>To every true Mourner over his own, and <hi>Zion</hi>'s ſins and ſorrows; eſpecially to ſuch in the Churches of Christ in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to whom the ſoul-ſinking ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of Miſtriſſe <hi>Deborah Huiſh,</hi> the Subject of the enſuing treatiſe, was well known: <hi>John Vernon,</hi> their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Chriſt, and Companion in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſſe, for <hi>Zions</hi> ſake, wiſheth grace for ſtrength in weakneſſe, to wait ſtill in weeping, and ſupplication until the times of refreſhment ſhall come from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, Amen. Even ſo come Lord Jeſus, come quickly, Amen.</head>
            <p>BEloved, you have herewith brought unto you an Olive-branch, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the floods abatement, and the reſt and ſafety of the ſoul that is entered into the Ark of God; the ranſome of a poor Priſoner out of the Pit indeed, in which there was no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: which will be, I know, the more welcome to ſome of you (I hope only to the praiſe and glory of God on high) becauſe you ſo long wept before his Heavenly Throne, and made your humble ſupplication to him almoſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fainting for her, who was bound of Satan ſo many years: yet that the
<pb facs="tcp:93284:9"/> height and depth, length and breadth of the love of God in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, might be the more admired of all, and magnified herein; And this Monument of mercy may remain in the Churches, throughout all ages, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſupport of ſuch as ſit in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſee no light: I am willing, (though moſt unworthy) to adde my mite towards the compleating this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the grace of God, extended to my poor (late diſtreſſed) Siſter, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſſe <hi>Deborah Huiſh;</hi> who is now made rich in Faith, through grace, and the wiſe Virgin-ſubject of this enſuing Relation: to the truth of which, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by her with much fear and joy, with trembling received, and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly written from her lips, by my dear Brother <hi>Allen,</hi> I can do no leſſe then bear my teſtimony, that (to thoſe who judge us faithful) it may out of the mouth of two or three witneſſes be eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>Yet becauſe many may be ſubject, with <hi>Thomas,</hi> called <hi>Dydimus,</hi> to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion what their eyes ſee not, and their fingers feel not; Theſe ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe any who do eſteem ſoul-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments of the greateſt conſequence,
<pb facs="tcp:93284:9"/> and deſire to be informed more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly in ſome part of the truth hereof, for the help of their own ſouls, or (as natural members of the body of Chriſt) to adminiſter ſome aſſiſtance unto their ſiſter, the ſubject of this enſuing trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, towards her continued walking uprightly and humbly with her God; That ſhe is the third Daughter of <hi>James Huiſh</hi> Eſquire of <hi>Sidbury,</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon;</hi> To whom God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to ſave, hath already granted an hopeful place in his houſe, to the joy of the faithful Churches in Chriſt Jeſus, who have more diligently then ſome in our dayes, weighed the truth of their high and heavenly calling, in the Balance of the ſanctuary, and inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into their ſoveraigne love to Chriſt, and ſutable converſation to the word of God, before they gave the right hand of Fellowſhip unto them: One of the three now is not, but having witneſſed unto death a good confeſſion before many witneſſes (and running beſt at laſt, even in theſe worſt dayes of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining, wherein Sun-ſhine and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Profeſſors are ſo puzzled, and put to their ſhifts, how to get with cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit again into their wider place, out
<pb facs="tcp:93284:10"/> of the faithful Churches) is fallen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep in Jeſus, whom God will bring with him at his coming, and her works ſhall follow her. In her ſtead hath God ſeaſonably raiſed this her Siſter to ſupply the breach made in the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble body of Chriſt, and in the Spirit of many faithful members, who (having ſorely lamented their too little im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of her, and ſome other dear Friends, lately taken from the evil to come (of whom this world, yea the Churches (or many amongſt them) yet in too much Fellowſhip with the world, I fear, were not worthy) will learn wiſedome (I truſt) to know their day, for treaſuring the Gold granted us, though through Earthen Veſſels; and better improve the ſmall remnant of Gods Elect, amongſt the great bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of outward <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who remain yet amongſt them.</p>
            <p>This bleſſed workmanſhip in Chriſt Jeſus, was through his good provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence (as her Siſter) from a Child in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the holy Scriptures, by their truely vertuous Mother: which edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation the Lord Sanctified, to make her very ſerious in her infancy, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining her from common fooliſh and
<pb facs="tcp:93284:10"/> vain communication. She was at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout fourteen years old, firſt ſenſibly aſſaulted by the tempter, and that fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, as you will perceive by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel: And from thenceforward you have her own Relation, to which I ſhall refer the ſerious Reader: but muſt remind many of the poor mourning Saints in <hi>Ireland,</hi> what they have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten heard from her; which may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps prove helpful to them, and other dejected ſouls, according to my ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt wiſh; to whoſe uſe her reſt and ſhelter (through rich grace, after a fourteen years ſad ſtormy Voyage, and bewildered wandering) is now Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated. For I judge her deep caſting down, and powerful raiſing up, was not onely for her ſake, and private uſes; but as a Pillar ſhould be erected for common caution againſt unbelief, and every ſin which coſt her ſo dear, and for encouragement out of ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal deeps, to look yet unto God's ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Temple, and to flee for hope and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge alwayes, onely to our one ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. <hi>And whoſo is wiſe, and will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe things: even they ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the loving kindneſſe of the Lord. Pſal.</hi> 107.43. Let us remember then
<pb facs="tcp:93284:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:16"/> what a meeting in, of almoſt all the complaints of the deſerted, darkened, and diſconſolate ones on Scripture re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, have refted on her poor ſoul, to the ſore afflicting alſo of ſome of yours, before the Throne of God, who did defer, but not deny, to anſwer your poor Prayers on her behalf: but at laſt hath heard, after you have heard her bemoaning herſelf, as <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>man</hi> the <hi>Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rahite, Pſalm</hi> 88.6. <hi>Thou hast layed me in the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>west Pit, in darkneſſe, in the deep; thy wrath lieth hard upon me; and thou haſt afflicted me with all thy Waves: I am afflicted and ready to die from my youth up, while I ſuffer thy terrours I am diſtracted, verſe</hi> 15. with Job 7.3, 4. <hi>So am I made to poſſeſſe months of Vanity; and wearyſome nights are appointed to me: when I lie down, I ſay, When ſhall I ariſe, and the night be gone? I am full of toſſings to and fro, unto the dawning of the day, mourning without the Sun,</hi> &amp;c. Chapter 30.28. with <hi>Hezekiah, reckoning till morning, that as a Lion ſo would he break all my bones from day even till night wilt thou make an end of me.</hi> Iſai. 38.13. <hi>And he hath both ſpoken to me, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath done it: I ſhall go ſoftly all my years in the bitterneſſe of my ſoul:</hi> Yea,
<pb facs="tcp:93284:16"/> with <hi>David</hi> ſhe might have ſaid, <hi>I m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y tell all my bones</hi> Pſal. 22.17. and ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in, <hi>my heart is ſmitten and withered like graſſe, ſo that I forget to eat my bread: by reaſon of the voice of my groaning, my bones cleave to my skin.</hi> And Pſal. 102.4, 5. and again, <hi>When I kept ſilence, my bones waxed old, through my roaring all the day long; for day and night thy hand was heavy upon me: my moiſture is turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the drought of Summer.</hi> Pſal, 32.3, 4. and with the Church, Lam. 3.18. <hi>My ſtrength and my hope is periſhed from the Lord:</hi> nay, with the deſperate hath ſhe not ſaid, in the hearing of many, <hi>There is no hope?</hi> Jer. 18.12. And with <hi>Cain, My puniſhment is greater then I can bear: Or, my Iniquity is greater then that it may be forgiven.</hi> I have ſinn'd unpardonably; you ſin in praying for me: I am undone and rejected; I know the very time when it was ſealed to me; I know it, I am ſure I am damned for ever, &amp;c. Oh! how have we been terrified together in our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblings on her behalf, who have ſeen her ſorrow, and diſability to ſpeak, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſometimes in ſuch like Language againſt her ſoul, and our ſeeking her Salvation; who was as a very fearful ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle
<pb facs="tcp:93284:17"/> pining away (even like to an Anatomy) before us: and how many of us, like the Friends of <hi>Job,</hi> came at firſt to mourn, and comfort her; but fainted, left off, relinquiſhed her, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding hopeleſſely! how hath a whole Church flagged in their Faith herein, (who reſolved to faſt and pray for her until deliverance) fainted and left off, yea drop'd away as weary, or aſhamed? how have ſome holy women (skilfull in mourning) aſſembled? what private indeavours by ſome obtaining her to their houſes, have been aſſayed? but all as water ſpilt upon the ground, in their eſteemes: Yea, to the glory of the grace of God alone herein, (who then loves to approve himſelf moſt favorable to his choſen, when they are moſt friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, helpleſs, deſtitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, &amp; moſt ſtand in need of ſuccour from him,) let me adde further this obſerva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion to yours, that a ſpecial Friend, whoſe affection led him further, and longer at a certainty then mine, or any I obſerved to weep for her, and to reprove others for fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and neglects of her before him, yet lately wrote from <hi>Ireland</hi> to me his deſpairing alſo concerning her; at the very interim God our God, who
<pb facs="tcp:93284:17"/> comforteth thoſe that are caſt down, was ſurely ſuccoring her, and incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his poor mourning fainting fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, whoſe Spirits were willing, though the Fleſh was weak, as he will further do in their ſight, unto publick admiration, for thoſe who in this evil time ſhall go forth weeping bearing pretious ſeed, according to his promiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.5, 6. and their Prayers in the fourth verſe: Yea, when there is but little Faith in the Earth; for alas, how have we, even we that were neareſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated alſo, left off our hope for this poor ſoul? Yea, how have I, to my ſhame, that had the charge of her, fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt herein! I muſt ſay indeed, to my abaſement, the weights and fear of her untimely end; the cares of keeping her from any Inſtrument to accompliſh it; and the dread of divers kinds that ſo long encompaſſed me concerning her, with the trouble we had to get her eat her bread, and to gaining her under hearing the word of God (which is more neceſſary) with the diſcouraging influence of living under the dayly droppings of thoſe many diſmal predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſhe uttered of her ſuddain and certain ruine &amp; deſtruction, after more
<pb facs="tcp:93284:18"/> then three years care of the kind a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and ſo many attempts and faintings: Alas, Paimed now at no more in my own mind, then to get her ſafe again delivered into her dear Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents hands, that my face might not be covered with ſhame, according to my fear of her untimely end, at ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from them: which being accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed by the good hand of God, (in our ſafe Voyage through his ſpecial grace, who led us and our little ones through his ſtormy deep, and after ſome hazzards landed us in ſafety; which I wiſh we may not let ſlip) alas, ſhe almoſt fell out of my memory, and was ſeldom in my Prayer; the Lord grant me the mercy of her earneſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications; for which <hi>Jobs</hi> Friends were made humbly to apply to him through like frailty towards him in his ſorrow, as I have reaſon to impute to my ſelf towards her herein.</p>
            <p>Thus hath the Lord our God ſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the pride of all glory, as he ſhall yet more publickely do unto his praiſe; and give grace to the humble, that they who glory, might onely glory in him, as the great end of his works of wonder, his great Salvations, and the
<pb facs="tcp:93284:18"/> operations of the Almighty in the Earth; that the faint, who relie on the Lord, may be revived; that youths, and every confident one may faint, and be humbled before him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Beloved, I beg the beſt effects in every heart, of this unſpeakable mercy, and to the glory of God in the higheſt, which I truſt is the onely end, why my poor Brother and Companion in mourning for our own ſins, and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and for yours alſo, which have the greateſt hand in hiding good things, yea the expected publicke Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations alſo from us, have agreed by the Advice of divers, who are alſo in the duſt for <hi>Zion,</hi> in this dark declining day, to recommend this token of good from God our Father and yours, unto you, towards the ſupport of your ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſouls, in his cloudy, gloomy houre, with our poor Epiſtles, full of affection to your pretious ſouls, affixed to this gratious earneſt of releaſing, drooping, dying Captives; who ſhall draw nigh to, and alone depend on God: And theſe I truſt ſhall come to every hand, with ſome effect of our earneſt Prayer, that the Lord God (Almighty to ſave) would accompany it, and greatly bleſs
<pb facs="tcp:93284:19"/> this grain of Muſtard ſeed, to make it grow and multiply unto the Faith and refreſhment of many, the abaſement of all, and the glorious exaltation of our King, who ſitteth at the right hand of the Father for us, and ſends the Comforter to ſuccour his feeble ones, in earneſt of his care of thoſe who caſt their care upon him, who onely hath the healing Medicines, and will ſurely (right ſoon) therewith viſit ſuch in every Nation; <hi>When all the proud,</hi> (how high ſoever) <hi>and they who ſtill do wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhall be as ſtubble before him.</hi> Mal. 4.1, 2. 2 Sam. 22.28. Oh that this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious anſwer to your ſupplications (in the beſt ſeaſon) might be now impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as a prop to uphold your hands, with the Rod of God therein, in this doubtful day, that <hi>Amalek</hi> may not prevail: Oh! wreſtle fervently in the unſpeakable priviledge of Faith; and (with Chriſt in your Armes) preſent your weepings, and ſpread your ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations before the Father in other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed caſes ſtill before you, by this incouragement; yea, let us improve it to publicke as well as private bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; for ſurely patterns of mercy ſhould be ſo made uſe of, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. And
<pb facs="tcp:93284:19"/> call for Faith in the path of them, as the moſt natural improvement. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. as well as to dread the expectation of a contrary portion, in the contrary path. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.5. And as the Declaration of Judgements, with the cauſe aſſigned, or the way in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, warneth all, and ſpeaks incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to none; ſo the manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of grace, and the path thereof, is an incouragement to all in the ſame path, and Spirit; which was eminently ſeen of old, in God's ſpecial preſence with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in driving back <hi>Jordan</hi> by his mighty Power for their preſent deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance (and their adverſaries deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) for which they erected Pillars of praiſe, to encourage the future Faith and hope of faithful ones that ſhould follow God fully, as his Servant <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> did: Yet could not <hi>Iſrael</hi> then have the leaſt ground to expect the dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving back of <hi>Jordan</hi> again, or remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving other difficulties, to have incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their retreat, or furthered any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane deſign, to which they were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſubject through unbelief: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in our dayes have any perſons ground to ſuppoſe (much leſſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude) that the Lords eminent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb facs="tcp:93284:20"/> in the high places of the field, ſcil. <hi>Naasby</hi> and other parts with his people, while they faithfully followed him, can now yeeld any incouragement to expect the like preſence of God, while they are turning back, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining from him.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, new appearances of the like glorious preſence with the truely humble followers of the Lord, (as the matter ſhould require) might again be ſafely expected from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty on high; who by the former no doubt manifeſted his right-hand Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for the ſtrengthening of the Faith and hope of all upright followers of him, according to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.8, 9, 10, 11. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.6, 7, 8, 9. and <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.5.</p>
            <p>And the very end of the Lords de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring to relieve <hi>Lazarus,</hi> whom he loved until he was dead, and laid in the Grave, and ſo no viſible hopes left unto his Diſciples touching his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent reſurrection, <hi>was to the intent they might believe, Joh.</hi> 11.15. not that he raiſed him onely; which every ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual beholder would believe: but that in future diſtreſſes, in their greateſt depths, they might depend on him by
<pb facs="tcp:93284:20"/> that proof of his Power to ſave to the uttermoſt.</p>
            <p>And no doubt <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, of whom its ſaid, <hi>They ſoon forgot his works,</hi> was ſo raviſh'd with the red Sea won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that they ever retained the Theory thereof, and could all of them relate it to any that ſhould ask them, either in matter or manner concerning it: but their not retaining the Teaching ſence thereof for uſe, in point of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for paſt deliverances, and of Faith in their future ſtraits, in the way of following God; left them to thoſe fears, through which they fell ſhort of obeying God, and entring <hi>Canaan.</hi> Now therefore, thou poor ſinking de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing ſoul, who ſitteſt in darkneſſe, and ſeeſt no light; Learn thou aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this pattern of mercy and long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering is to manifeſt to thee, that the Lord's thoughts are higher then thine; that ſo thy ſoul may be encouraged, under the ſentence of death, by reaſon of ſin, through believing, to have life and hope in him: If thou ſayeſt, Is any ſorrow like my ſorrow? Yea, is any ſin like my ſin? and truely conſidereſt the ſorrow of this ſoul, and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate ſin of a ſecret Deviliſh mind,
<pb facs="tcp:93284:21"/> in this caſe related, with her confident expectation of Hell thereupon, on the one hand; and the gratious pity and acceptance ſhe found from Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing embraced by him as in open Arms, ſo ſoon as truely perſwaded humbly to come unto him, on the other hand: I hope it will ſilence ſuch ſuggeſtions di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſing thee, and ſeal to thy comfort the truth of that promiſe, that is ſo richly confirmed to her, <hi>John</hi> 6.37. Now if any accepted through grace, ſhould abate in their Faith, becauſe their preſent Feaſt ſeems not ſo full, nor their entertainment ſo ſenſibly free, as that whereat this ſoul now ſits ſo fully refreſh'd; I truſt, if (in their weakneſſe) ſupporting grace be ſurely afforded, and they found waiting in their Fathers houſe and affaires, that word ſhall ſuffice to balance them from fainting and fretting at ſuch grace to others, recorded, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.31, 32. And that her years of ſorrow ſhall be by ſuch conſidered, according to <hi>Pſ.</hi> 90.15. <hi>Make us glad, according to the dayes wherein thou hast afflicted us.</hi> And oh! that this might warn all of every ſin, and neglect, which being bound on her ſoul, have been found ſo long and
<pb facs="tcp:93284:21"/> ſo heavy a load: but how ſhall I utter the evil and bitter effects thereof, better then by asking the ſerious ſoul, what debaſing, defiling, and enſlaving miſery himſelf hath experienced, as the effect of but eating the forbidden fruit at firſt, and that by another? Yea, with deſign to be made more Spiritual, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have good mens good meanings excuſed the leaſt tranſgreſſion or er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror: This treatiſe will tell you alſo what thoſe poor ſouls loſe, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect, or are ſlighty in family-endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, in the word and Prayer; in both which ſhe found more benefit (through grace) then in more able publick Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations, under which ſome can ſcarcely profit, through their horrid ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect herein; and will have poor kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Children, and Servants, one day complain of their loſs, by living under the ſhadow of ſuch, few of whom will ſhine as Stars in the Firmament, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the promiſe, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3. if they perſiſt in the neglect thereof, and forget that exhortation, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.4.</p>
            <p>That I may not make an end of theſe poor hints, towards the improving this mercy, without remembring the Mourners in <hi>Dublin,</hi> of another (elect
<pb facs="tcp:93284:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:27"/> one I truſt) whoſe ſecret ſins, ſtanding in the light of God's countenance, humbly waited for his Salvation, ſo many ſolemne dayes among them, poſſeſſing Months and years of ſorrow, and they of tears for her poor ſoul, who alas is not now found in the way of the true converts path, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.17, 18, 19. And will ſurely, as <hi>Jacob,</hi> have her fears renewed, for building ſhort of <hi>Bethel,</hi> when new troubles ſhall incompaſſe her, and the Courts (ſhort of the Lord's) prove unable to comfort: Oh that this effectual expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of breaking the bands of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan for another (who was with leſſe hope and expectation ſo oft joyned with her in your interceſſions) may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new your ſtrength in ſupplication for her; whoſe ſeeming weanedneſſe from the world, and the weights of ſuch vain Company as now beſet her, ſometimes adminiſtred hopes, that ſhe would never be aſhamed to chuſe affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the people of God, nor be otherwayes then as <hi>Heſter</hi> in the Court of the miſs-informed and enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt them. Oh! that by fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent wreſtlings ſhe might be raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from every falſe reſt; and as being
<pb facs="tcp:93284:27"/> plucked by the Arm of the Almighty, as a fire-brand out of the fire, might be ſaved from all vain pomp, infecting Company, and cuſtomes; the fury of the higheſt of men, and from ſmoother temptations more near unto her, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing her liberty in neglects; and ſo beguiling her of her choiſeſt good, as the Tempter beguiled <hi>Eve:</hi> yea, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I fear with the ſtumbling-Block of the falls of ſome, (found in the wayes of God) improved to the utmoſt in this evil day, to prejudice ſouls with them; ſo that many indeed are now offended in Chriſt, and I much long that a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain love to his holy wayes, might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve her from that evil: According to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.11, 165. Yea, let the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Gideon</hi> be remembered, to oblige us herein; who unweariedly with unparalell'd uprightneſſe, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth his labour of love to the Lord, and to us in the Lord unto death, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting much in the perſwaſion, that his deareſt relation (and Children left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him amongſt us) would never more be beſet with the unexpected ſnares of that ſort now encompaſſing; but be in the conſtant ſpecial care of the moſt faithful of the Saints; delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:93284:28"/> herſelf with <hi>David,</hi> in thoſe that excel in vertue.</p>
            <p>Me thinks this mercy improved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right (without diverſion) may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended alſo, to Adminiſter reviving to the poor Priſoners for righteouſneſſe ſake (who (onely in a way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) ſhall humbly wait for the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God) notwithſtanding the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke reproach caſt upon them, by men of corrupt minds: For behold, the hand of the Lord, who led <hi>Joſeph</hi> through Impriſonment, ſlanders, and many difficulties, and thereby fitted him for further ſpecial publick relief and benefit; (though his Brethren meant not ſo, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.20) is not yet ſhortened, but here ſhewed gloriouſly in the ranſome of this ſometimes poor hopeleſſe Priſoner, that diſtreſſed ones may have hope in him, <hi>Who cauſeth light to ariſe out of darkneſſe;</hi> leading his Priſoners forth in his ſet time and ſeaſon; who will ſay ſhortly to his Captives, <hi>Shew your ſelves,</hi> according to <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49.9. And ſurely this may help to ſuccour alſo the whole <hi>Zion</hi> of God; though ſhe be ready to ſay, <hi>My God hath forgotten me.</hi> Oh that therefore that travel ſpoken of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.6, 7, 8. &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:93284:28"/> were now begun by all that have their hearts heavy loaden, with their own (and others) Iniquities; and that ſuch might never hold their peace, nor give the Lord reſt: but in the ſtrength of <hi>Jacob,</hi> by weeping and ſupplication, wreſtle with the Mighty one of <hi>Jacob,</hi> till he return in pitty unto <hi>Zion,</hi> to their own ſouls, and to all the diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed who wait upon him; and to the ſtopping the mouth of all Iniquity in the Nations (ſo lately reſcued by his hand) even till the dry bones live, and the heart of thoſe that weep now, greatly rejoyce, and flouriſh like an herb; and the hand of the Lord be known towards his Servants, and his indignation towards his Enemies; yea, to that effect in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.12. For thus ſaith the Lord, Behold, I will extend peace to her as a River, &amp;c. and <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.21. And their Nobles ſhall be of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, &amp;c. That the glory of the Lord may be redeemed in the Land.</p>
            <p>Let us ſtill wait on the Arm of the Lord, who cauſed <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> to be reſtleſs in the night, till he had read the records of the Chronicles of the good ſervice of <hi>Mordecai,</hi> to the changing his heart from his wicked decree, and
<pb facs="tcp:93284:29"/> turning it againſt his <hi>treacherous Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers;</hi> and who have taught us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his hand upon the haughty of old, and to plead it in future diſtreſſe, as in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 51.9. <hi>Awake, awake, put on ſtrength, Oh Arm of the Lord! awake, as in the antient dayes,</hi> &amp;c. For hereby hath he gratiouſly given us a freſh proof of his Power, to performe whatever may make to our relief and comfort in every condition, whether we be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed with publicke, or private diſtreſſes: wherefore I have ſomewhat enlarged upon this opportunity of Printing on this occaſion, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes I love not, thus variouſly to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove this inſtance (though ſome men may eſteem them unneceſſary diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) for the begetting of Faith in God by this Example of dread, and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement; which can onely inable to meet him acceptably in humiliation, and before the decree be gone forth, as againſt <hi>Shil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> of old, and <hi>Judah,</hi> who periſhed with the ſignes of God's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in their hand, through their not obſerving aright, to Sanctifie his name, who had made them ſo ſtrong and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſeful againſt their Adverſaries. And ſeeing the Lord alone can heal our ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:93284:29"/> and our wound, and the breach upon us, which is wide as the Sea; let every true Mourner humbly approach before him, on the behalf of our ſelves, and whole <hi>Zion,</hi> the Prophets, Rulers, Judges, Laws, Cuſtomes of theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; &amp; on the behalf of the afflicted, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, unbelieving, divided, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by liable to be deſtroyed people; and to turn the heart of thoſe that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, and ready to do evil, becauſe it is in the Power of their hands to do it: for now all men almoſt ſee our ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and our wound, how fooliſh ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Phyſitians and our falſe refuges have proved.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore now ceaſe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from <hi>Babylon, Egypt, Aſhur;</hi> Horſes, Armies, fenced Cities, &amp;c. But alſo from thoſe other fair ſhews in the fleſh, to which ſome fearful Friends would compel us to conform, which have too oft deceived us: Neither let us humour the luſts of men and multitudes, nor be found in the indirect path of fretting proud wrath, envying and grudging one againſt another; nor in raſh inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, ſubmitting to traditions, tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing, &amp;c. But in deep humiliation, and brokenneſſe of ſoul, let us be as
<pb facs="tcp:93284:30"/> Doves of the Valley, every one mourning over his Iniquities, which is the moſt hopeful path of refreſhment from his preſence, who hath hereby ſhewed us his right hand; which will certainly relieve, and that right ſoon, thoſe that truely ſowe in teares; for according to his faithful word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.5, 6. <hi>He that goeth forth and weepeth, bearing pretious ſeed, ſhall doubtleſſe return again with rejoycing, bringing his ſheaves with him:</hi> When the Bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of pride ſhall wither, and the bands of mockers will be made ſtrong: Let my ſoul and yours be imbarked with thoſe that weep this day before the Lord, chuſing affliction with his people, rather then with thoſe who rejoyce now, and are not ſenſible <hi>of the afflictions of Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph;</hi> but make merry with the nakedneſſe of <hi>Noah:</hi> and that the Counſel given us for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.20, 21. may be accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with the reſidue of the Spirit for our gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and ſuccour, as being given us to be a word of gratious Counſel for ſuch a day as this: And that though Satan be ſeen yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to fall, as lightening from Heaven; We may chiefly rejoyce, in that our names are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Book of Life. And now to be ſtill freely admitted with this precious ſoul, to that Feaſt that fadeth not for evermore; is the humble and earneſt deſire (on the behalf of himſelf, and all Saints) of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The unworthiest of thoſe who yet ſtand by Faith, through the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding grace of God,</hi> JOHN VERNON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:93284:30"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou haſt here preſented to thy view, and ſerious conſideration; an eminent pattern of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'s faithfulneſſe, in fulfilling that good word, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.20. <hi>A bruiſed reed ſhall he not break, and ſmoaking Flax ſhall he not quench, till he ſend forth Judgem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt unto Victory.</hi> Which may help to confirme thee in that great truth, that there is nothing too hard for him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.14. compared with <hi>Job.</hi> 42.2. Who can, and will work when he pleaſeth, and none ſhall let it, <hi>Eſai.</hi> 43.13. Neither the height of Satan's malice, nor the depth of ſinners miſery, can hinder the free Communication of his mercy to ſuch as look for Salvation from him, (to which all are freely invited) <hi>Eſai.</hi> 45.22.</p>
            <p>And although I judge, two ſuch teſtimonies as are annexed to this treatiſe, ſuffic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie ſuch as know them, of the truth of what they aſſert: Yet I having been (by the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God) for ſome years paſt, an eye and ear-witneſs in the Family, to the ſad and deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition of this poor ſoul, now inrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from above, (who is the ſubject of the inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Narrative) I have thought meet to adde my mite, and thereby ſignifie my conſent to the truth of what is contained in the two fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Epiſtles, concerning the late diſtreſſed ſtate of that Daughter of <hi>Abraham,</hi> now loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the loving kindneſſe of the Lord. She hath been indeed for a long ſeaſon in the depth of miſery (as to her inward man) being bound in affliction, and Iron, by the Tempter, who
<pb facs="tcp:93284:31"/> was ſuffered to aſſault, and buffet her poor ſoul even to deſpair of all help or hope; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her often to conclude, that her ſins were greater then could be forgiven: but that God, who is rich in mercy, hath appeared gratiouſly (in his own time) to hear, and anſwer the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of his people in her behalf, in relieving her poor ſoul, and making her to ſee, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to his praiſe, that the former ſuggeſtions concerning him (and her ſouls irrecoverable eſtate) was from the Father of lies; whoſe work it is, to intice and tempt ſouls unto ſin, and then wound them in the ſence of it, endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by all means to perſwade ſuch, that they have out-ſinn'd the mercy of God.</p>
            <p>But behold here the God of truth, whoſe grace is ſufficient to ſupport under, and deliver effectually from ſuch ſoul-ſinking conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, making Satan appear to be (what indeed he is) <hi>a Lier.</hi> And ſeaſonably ſuccouring this dejected deſpairing ſoul, who for a long time had the ſentence of death in her ſelf, and was far from expecting that bleſſed iſſue that is fince brought forth in her ſoul (by the mighty Power, and naked Arm of the Lord) who hath hereby helped her to ſee what little reaſon ſhe had, or hath, to truſt in her ſelf; and the ſure ground he hath now given her, to ſtay on him as the living God, who raiſeth the dead; ſo that ſhe is now made able <hi>(yea willing)</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, <hi>His great gooddeſſe that hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered her from ſo great a death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>and doth deliver; and is ſtill helped to hope and truſt that he will yet deliver, and ſtrengthen her Faith, to quench all the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y darts of the Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold yet further the exceeding Riches
<pb facs="tcp:93284:31"/> of God's grace not a little illuſtrated by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting free this Priſoner, ſometimes even paſt hope in her own (and ſome others) apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: She that was for a long ſeaſon ſadly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding with the diſtreſſed Church, in <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.18. <hi>That her ſtrength and hope was periſh'd from the Lord,</hi> Is now ſaying with <hi>Saul,</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 9.6. <hi>Lord, what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> And with the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> thankfully inquiring, <hi>What ſhall I render unto the Lord for all his benefits to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me?</hi> And in ſome meaſure inabled to reſolve with him, <hi>To take the Cup of Salvation, and to call upon the name of the Lord, as Pſal.</hi> 116.12, 13, 14. And ſhe, that was lately (in her own eſteem) not ſo good as a Dog; yea (to uſe her own words) worſe then any Devil, is now, <hi>(By the Father of mercies, and God of all conſolations) made meet to be partaker of the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the Saints in light:</hi> The ſad ſentences ſhe had oft paſt upon her ſelf (in the ſenſe of her ſins) being now gratiouſly reverſed by her Heavenly Father, who hath ſet her feet in a large place: ſo that now, if ſin, Satan, her own <hi>corruptions,</hi> or any other ſpiritual Adverſary, comes to lay any thing to her Clarge, ſhe may be ready (the Lord aſſiſting) to produce her pardon; and able to ſay from bleſſed expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33, 34. <hi>It is God that ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth; who is he that condemneth? that it is Chriſt that died, yea rather that is riſen again, who is even at the right hand of God, who alſo maketh interceſſion for us</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I hope this eminent inſtance of his grace abounding above the abounding of ſin, (added to other Examples of this kind recorded in his holy word) will help to ſupport and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour
<pb facs="tcp:93284:32"/> ſome poor ſouls under the like diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to hope in his mercy, who waits to be gratious; and ſurely he hath gratious ends in affording this (and ſuch like) delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, which greatly concernes all perſons to labour to underſtand, and improve aright.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, let ſinners of all ſorts (both in <hi>Zion</hi> and out of it) from the inſuing narrative, take notice of the ſad, enſnaring, and ſoul-deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nature of ſin, and the wages of it, which this poor ſoul (as ſhe feared) had certainly found to be eternal death, had not the <hi>God of grace, (whoſe loving kindneſſe is better then life) cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her to hear the joyful ſound of the voice of the Son of God, that her ſoul might live, John</hi> 5.25.</p>
            <p>Secondly, from the conſideration of the mercy ſhe hath obtained, let poor ſinners be incited and incouraged, to come unto God through Chriſt for mercy, who knows how to <hi>multiply pardon</hi> to the worſt of ſinners, as in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55.7. with <hi>Nehe.</hi> 9 17. Eſpecially let ſuch as are inquiring the way to <hi>Zion,</hi> with their faces thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therward, <hi>Though with trembling hands &amp; hearts;</hi> and all that are planted in the houſe of the Lord, be incouraged to wait upon God, who will in no wiſe caſt out thoſe that come unto him. Let the firſt of theſe labour to <hi>look to the Lord, that they may be enlightened:</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm</hi> 34.5.</note> And let the other be confirm'd, in the experience they have had of his great goodneſſe, that ſo God may have all the glory from both, as a Fruit of this ſpecial favour afforded to this his hand-maid, in ſo ſignal a return of many Prayers; for which proportionable praiſes ſhould wait for, (and be duly rendered unto) our God in <hi>Zion,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:93284:32"/> who is a preſent help in the needful time of trouble. I ſhall not adde, but to intreat thee to read, and conſider well, before thou cenſureſt, (or ſeeme to deſpiſe) the enſuing ſubject, as the day of ſmall things; but labour rather, to weigh the worth of this mercy in the <hi>Balance of the Sanctuary;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That ſo thou mayeſt underſtand the end and uſe of it, and be help'd to improve it aright, to the praiſe of the Author of every good and perfect gift, and the profit of thine own ſoul; that ſo thou mayeſt be able to ſay with the Prophet of old, <hi>Micha</hi> 7.18. <hi>Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth Iniquity, and paſſeth by the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of the remnant of his heritage! that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth not his anger for ever, becauſe he delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mercy:</hi> And from thence be incouraged to wait upon him for the fulfilling that faithful word, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 40.29, 30, 31. <hi>He giveth power to the faint, and to them that have no might, he increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſtrength,</hi> &amp;c. Compared with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.14. <hi>Wait on the Lord, and be of good courage, and he ſhall ſtrengthen thine heart: wait, I ſay, on the LORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ROB. DOYLY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93284:33"/>
            <head>To all, both ſmall and great, that have either taſted of the rich grace of God, or deſire to be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers thereof, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Men, and Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough we were very much ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, both to the perſon and ſtate of this gratious hand-maid of the Lord (the ſubject of this enſuing treatiſe, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of her ſore bondage, and captivity of Spirit; and ſo had no ſhare with thoſe that in a ſolemn manner (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly on her account) ſympathized, ſighed, and groaned to God in her behalf: Yet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving now through grace (we trust, we may ſay) to the advantage of our ſouls, heard out of her own mouth, in the midſt of the Congregation to which we belong, (to wit, the Church of Christ at <hi>Dalwood</hi> in <hi>Dorſet</hi>) the wonderful deliverance which God hath wrought f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r her poor ſoul: We cannot, but in a ſpecial manner rejoyce with her, and bleſſe the Most High for his unſpeakable mercy.</p>
            <p>That this work is of the Lord, and ſoul-work indeed; it ſpeaks for it ſelf to all the wiſe in heart. That the Relation is very faithfully made, We do hereby teſtify, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:93284:33"/> (as we ſaid before) heard out of her own mouth the ſubſtance of the whole; who then (in point of circumſtance) would have been more particular and large, had not time, and the earnest ſollicitation of a near Relation of hers (whom God had uſed in ſome good meaſure, as an Inſtrument of her enlargement) concurr'd to prevent her.</p>
            <p>Two or three of our obſervations, while ſhe related this unto us, we cannot but mind the Reader of.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> That having layen ſo long (as the Narrative mentioneth) under ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>error of ſoul; And having now newly received her enlargement, ſhe was ſo filled with admiration at the exceeding Riches of the grace of God in her deliverance, as that it many times ſtopt her Spirit, for a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable ſeaſon: and ſhe could in all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) have dwelt long between ſentence and ſentence, in a ſecret, inward ſilent lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of her ſoul to God in thanks-giving.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> We obſerved very much faithfulneſs, and tenderneſſe of ſoul in her faithfulneſſe; in that ſhe dwelt as long upon, and ſpake as largely to, the darkest paſſages of her blaſpheming God, and maligning his people (though doubtleſſe the remembring of ſuch things was with grief of ſoul to her) as in ſpeaking to the highest manifeſtations of
<pb facs="tcp:93284:34"/> the grace of God, in her preſent enjoyments of her ſoul; expreſſing her ſelf to the ſame effect with the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 5.20.</hi> Where ſin abounded, grace did much more abound.</p>
            <p>Tenderneſſe, In that with very much circumſpection ſhe endeavoured to keep even to a tittle, both to the matter and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Gods dealing with her: And if at any time ſhe (or any elſe, who knew her in her afflicted eſtate, and endeavoured to help her memory) ſlipt, ſhe would preſently correct both herſelf and them, and ſtate the matter aright, and in its place, before ſhe would let it paſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> That her rejoycing was mixed with much holy fear and trembling; ſtill eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf as a poor Worm before the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God of Iſrael, though exalted to many glorious Priviledges through his rich grace.</p>
            <p>We might ſpeak further, what we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved of the crafty wiles of Satan, in the manner of his working with her poor ſoul; first training her on from ſin to ſin, and from degree to degree, ſtill foreſtalling her with a perſwaſion that ſhe was already both in the ſin, and in the degree which he would train her into: And when by that ſlight he had got her further on, then
<pb facs="tcp:93284:34"/> perſwading her, that ſhe had out-ſinned all grace; ſo endeavouring to deſtroy all hope. And indeed this is our common obſervation of the working of Satan, (to wit) That to perſons that are in a wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſtate, and inſenſible thereof, he leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſin, and wideneth grace, that they may run the more greedily in their evil wayes; making out to them, as if the gate of grace, opening to life, were wide enough for all perſons to paſſe in at, with all their ſins. But to thoſe perſons that are brought to the ſight of their ſins, and their wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedneſſe thereby, he wideneth ſin, and narroweth grace; making out to them, as though their ſins (though not againſt the Holy Ghoſt) are greater then can be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: in both which, he is a grievous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver.</p>
            <p>Alſo we might here more largely ſhew the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what ſubtle ſlights Satan uſed with this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the Lord, to hinder her obedience to the Commandments of Christ, and particularly to that of Baptiſme; preſenting it as a poor low thing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But as to that, we ſhall in this place onely give thee notice, that when ſhe was in the highest revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and had the most ſealing Teſtimonies of the grace of God to her ſoul, She was then led forth most affectionately to own the Lord Jeſus in that deſpiſed Ordinance and appointment of his; as may be ſeen more at large in the Narrative it ſelf; ſuitable to that word given to <hi>Paul,</hi> after his great
<pb facs="tcp:93284:35"/> revelations of grace, <hi>Act. 22.16.</hi> where it was ſaid unto him by the Spirit, And now why tarriest thou? ariſe, and be Baptized, and waſh away thy ſins, calling on the name of the Lord.</p>
            <p>What we ſhall further ſay in this matter, ſhall be onely to ſignifie, that upon the whole (ſhe deſiring to give up her ſelf to the Lord, to walk in all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments blameleſſely, and to have fellowſhip and communion with his people, in the exerciſe of all the Goſpel-Priviledges inſtituted by Christ their King and Head, for his Body the Church; and particularly with this Congregation, to watch (and be watched over by them) She was with univerſal ſatisfaction accepted, and accordingly Baptized, and received. Many fierce Aſſaults hath the Enemy of her peace made against her, ſince the chain of her bondage was broken: but againſt all, the Lord hath made very gracious proviſion through the word; bringing home (through the Power of his Spirit) many ſull promiſes to her ſoul, and eſtabliſhing her through them.</p>
            <p>To the God of Peace, who (through his own Rich and free love, after many years horrour of ſoul) is become her Peace; do we deſire to commit all his choſen Veſſels to honour, for his calling in his ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon unto, and for his eſtabliſhing and growth of thoſe that are called in the truth, as it is in Jeſus: which Jeſus we deſire to own as our King, our Crown, and hope of glory; and to whoſe appearing with that glorious Kingdom, we deſire to be dayly better prepared: That at his coming we may have the honour to be of that bleſſed number that ſhall wait upon him with Hallelujahs, ſinging forth praiſe, glory and honour to the Father and to the Lamb, for ever and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Friends and Brethren in the hope of the Goſpel,</hi> Hen. Parſon. Jo. Owen. Jam. Hill. <hi>1658.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93284:35"/>
            <head>The Captive taken from the ſtrong, or a true Relation of the gratious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe of Miſtriſs DEBORAH HUISH, (by the Arme of the Almighty) from under the power of the Tempter, by whoſe firy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts ſhe had been ſorely vexed for about fourteen years; as it was faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully written from her own Mouth, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout fourteen years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go I was caſt into deep deſpair, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of blaſphemous thoughts caſt into my mind, when I was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying my ſelf to the reading the word of the Lord; which thoughts were deſpiſing, ſlighting, and contemning God, his word, works, and wayes: with which being frequently aſſaulted, I came to gather Concluſions, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93284:36"/> God had paſt an irrecoverable decree againſt me for my final condemnation; and though I had reluctancy in my heart againſt ſuch thoughts, yet many times I did give my conſent to them, and approved of them; and from thence came to have great horrour ſeize upon me, for many dayes and nights after. Cauſing me to conclude theſe to be but the fore-runners of that great deſtruction from the Lord, which I judged was prepared for me: and ſuch thoughts as theſe at firſt were (continually almoſt) born in with great weight upon my ſoul: about which time my Siſter <hi>Anne Vernon</hi> (then <hi>Huiſh</hi>) obſerving my dejected frame, deſired to know the cauſe; I told her then that God had rejected me for my blaſphemous thoughts I had conceived againſt him, worſe then any Devil; but my Siſter indeavored to perſwade me, theſe thoughts were not mine, but the Devil's: this gave me ſome reſpit for a little time. bur I was ſuddenly aſſaulted again, and have continued under ſuch aſſaults everſince, more or leſs, till the time hereafter ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, when the Lord of his free Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93284:36"/> began to make way for my eſcape.</p>
            <p>I do alſo remember that I had not onely deſpiſing, ſlighting thoughts of God, but alſo of his people, calling them in my thoughts (though not with my lips) lyars.</p>
            <p>But when I did think I conſented to ſuch thoughts, then horrour would ſeize upon me, even to overwhelme me: and in this condition I remained till my going into <hi>Ireland,</hi> which was about <hi>June</hi> 1654.</p>
            <p>After my coming there, the Lord vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited me with the Small-pox; and in that time of ſickneſſe I thought I had ſome refreſhment from the Lord, by conſulting his word; but was ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after aſſaulted with more and worſe blaſphemous thoughts then ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and then did verily believe I was poſſeſſed with the Devil, and did think I talked with him, and heard him ſay, that God loved to torment and bring miſery upon his Creatures; which thoughts were ſo preſſing upon me, that I was ready to wiſh the deſtruction of the Almighty; and did to my think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hate him; crying out (in the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many) I am undone to Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93284:37"/> and ſo remaineth till lately: And ſo dreadful were theſe (laſt mentioned) thoughts to my ſoul, that from that time I concluded, I had committed the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I did onely think I had, but now was confirmed in it, and began to think I had really trampled under foot the blood of Jeſus Chriſt, and had done deſpite to the Spirit of grace; and thence concluded that nothing now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, but a fearful looking for of vengeance, that ſhould devour the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary: and this put me into unexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible torments night and day, thinking the Devil would come and fetch me away, and I believed I was certain of it: and when any went to pray for me, I thought that haſtened my deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore I hated them for it, and had in my mind many ſad wiſhes as to thoſe that prayed for me, count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hell my portion, and that I ſhould by ſuch means be ſooner cut off, and that they ſin'd in praying: I having ſin'd againſt the holy Ghoſt, thought they ought to hate me, but not pray for me: I did alſo think I alwayes heard a fearful ſound in my ears, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93284:37"/> when it was windy or rainy weather, and then thought I ſhould be caſt into Hell preſently: which made an unexpreſſable torment of mine to think of it; and yet under all the means uſed to ſeek God for me, I found no benefit.</p>
            <p>But at <hi>Dublin,</hi> when dayes were ſet apart, to ſeek God for me, I dreaded thoſe dayes, above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thinking verily that God was ingaged in honour, to come out againſt me in fierce indignation, as alſo againſt ſuch as ſought him on my behalf: and I did many times think the Lord in a way of judgement would turn me into ſome filthy hateful Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or other, as a Memorial of his juſt diſpleaſure againſt me; and all the time that prayers were put up for me (which was very frequent in <hi>Dublin,</hi> as alſo diſcourſes very often with me) I could not perceive that any ever took the leaſt hold on my heart, but ſtill I had that Scripture oft on my thoughts:<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.5.</note> 
               <hi>By terrible things in righteouſneſſe wilt thou anſwer them:</hi> which I underſtood to be ſome anſwer in a way of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as to me: I had alſo that Scripture
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93284:38"/> much on my heart:<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.31, 32.</note> 
               <hi>He that ſins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holy Ghoſt, ſhall never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given in this world, nor in that which is to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as to reading the Scriptures, my heart was much averſe to it; oneiy ſometimes out of compaſſion to others I did read, and ſometimes did mind them what the caſting off the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures had coſt me, who is now rejected for ever, wiſhing them to take heed of the like: but it was very ſeldome that I did this, and long ere I could bring my heart to it.</p>
            <p>I do alſo remember when I lived at <hi>Clantarfe</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and uſed to go to <hi>Dublin</hi> ſometimes, to hear the word; I have often thought, when I went, I ſhould be deſtroyed ere I came back again; and when I did hear, I ſtrove all I could to forget what I heard, or read, having my expectations of Hell ſo heightened by all ſuch means, that I could not endure it; &amp; would have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven any thing I might never have gone to have heard, or prayed more, it did ſo increaſe the torments of my ſoul. And when I came into the place where I uſed to hear, I ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll expected to hear
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93284:38"/> ſome ſudden voice from Heaven, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring my deſtruction; and did think many times that the wind aroſe juſt as I came to that place to hear, and did believe the Lord muſt needs appear in judgement againſt me for coming, and ſitting as one of his people among them, whom I in my heart hated: and would long that the duties might be ended, that I might be free from thoſe feares that were upon me while there.</p>
            <p>I do alſo remember that almoſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing did afright me; either a clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy day, the Sun or Moon Eclipſed, or the Suns riſing red in a morning, or the wind blowing high: All theſe I thought were ſignes of my deſtruction, that I did believe the Lord would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute upon me for my hatred againſt him and his wayes. And indeed ſuch an inveterate hate I had againſt him, that I judged, I loathed and abhorred the doing good to any, ſaying in my ſelf, that the Lord would damn and deſtroy me; and why ſhould I do any good? I alſo wiſhed many times, I had never been born, or had never had eyes to ſee, or ears to hear, or elſe had been made the moſt contemptible
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93284:39"/> Creature in the world, becauſe when they die there is an end of them; but when I die, my miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry then begins. I alſo wiſhed, I might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ever hear any one ſpeak more from the Scriptures to me, for I reckoned all that had ſpoken to me, either in ſickneſſe or in health, would be witneſſes againſt me, and ſo aggravate my ſin and miſery, becauſe I had ſuch warnings, and had not hark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened to them, but to the Devil; and eſpecially Mr. <hi>Patient,</hi> a Miniſter of the word in <hi>Dublin,</hi> coming to me in the time of my ſickneſſe, and ſpeaking of the great danger of an impenitent ſtate if the Lord ſhould cut the thrid of life, that ſuch perſons would drop imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately into Hell, the which he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to demonſtrate to me, that I thought he would be the principal witneſſe againſt me, of all that had ſpoke with me: ſo that I now ſaw my ſelf without hope, and the mercy of the Lord utterly taken from me, not as it was from <hi>Saul,</hi> but far worſe; I having ſinned againſt far greater light, and more warnings, and after ſuch taſts and enlightnings to fall away, it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to renew me again unto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93284:39"/> but concluded I ſhould ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly be deſtroyed, and that without remedy.</p>
            <p>This being my caſe, I remember, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my ſickneſs in <hi>Dublin</hi> aforemention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, what fretful hateful thoughts I had of God, ſaying in my mind, I wil do this or that in deſpight of God, and I could not think otherwiſe; and ſuch a hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful bent of ſpirit I had againſt the Lord, that I was oft ready to ſay in my heart, I will curſe God and die; and at laſt through the ſtrength of temptation I was ſo far prevailed upon, as I did in my thoughts curſe God and all I could think of that belonged to him, and then concluded my ſelf damned indeed, and that I was ſure of it: and then ſaid to my ſelf, I am now ſure I have committed the ſin againſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, which is unpardonable, and ſhould now to Eternity be tormented with the Devil and his Angels: and this ſorely afflicted and overwhelmed me, in ſo much that I was once tempted to caſt my ſelf down out of a window to kill my ſelf, onely the dread of Hell I thought deterred me from it: I did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſtrive to put horrour out of my mind
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93284:40"/> all I could, by enjoying outward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, but alas theſe were all imbitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me, when I ſaw the end of ſuch comforts: I did alſo ſometimes endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to divert theſe thoughts by buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe I ſet my ſelf about; but being ſometimes hot at work, I ſhould have the heat of Hell-fire thereby brought to my mind, and the terribleneſſe of that repreſented to me. But the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt eaſe I had in theſe diſtracting ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, was by ſetting my ſelf upon buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but found my ſelf ſo continually harraſed with thoughts of Hell, that my heart grew hard, and ſtupid, ſo that though I knew that was my portion, yet I was unſenſible of it, unleſſe at ſometimes, when horrour would vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently break in upon me, eſpecially at ſuch times as I was forced to go to hear, when I ſtill expected God to witneſſe againſt me by ſome ſore judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from Heaven, which (upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dark and ſtormy day eſpecially) I expected, and did oft times judge I ſaw flaſhes of fire come upon my face, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me in mind of that horrible pit of darkneſſe I ſhould one day fall into: And many times when I went to bed, I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93284:40"/> have been afraid to ſleep, leſt I ſhould be caſt into Hell ere I waked again: to prevent which, I have oft reſolved not to ſleep, onely ſometimes through a ſtupid ſenſleſſe frame I ſhould lye down and ſleep, not thinking of my danger: but when I waked, I wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed I was not in Hell; yet could not be thankful for it, but ſtill thought I ſhould be there ſhortly; and though I lived never ſo long, yet to be there at laſt would ſwallow up all this time, as if it had not been; and all the comforts I now enjoyed, would but aggravate my ſorrow and miſery then, when I ſhall be deprived of all, and ſuffer for what I now enjoy: upon which account, all my comforts were bitter to me; and when I taſted any thing, I ſtill thought what I ſhould taſt ere long in Hell, which made me hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able to eat my meat, for I ſhould thus reaſon: Why ſhould I eat and drink, when I am in dayly expectation of being caſt into Hell? and then was that Scripture brought to mind,<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 57.20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>The wicked are like the troubled Sea that cannot reſt, whoſe waters caſt up mire and dirt: there is no peace to the wicked:</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93284:41"/> And many times when I have been at work, ſuddain flaſhes of Hell have been as it were darted into my ſoul; ſo that I have run out of the room where I was, and would have run out of the Lords preſence alſo, if I could: but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, my foul had no refuge to flye to from him, nor can I remember that I had a heart ſo much as to ſeek for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, onely in ſome great diſtreſſes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I think I have uſed the words, LORD HAVE MERCY UPON ME, but without any hope or expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of obtaining what I prayed for; but concluded God would not ſave me, unleſſe he would deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his word: and though an Angel from Heaven ſhould have told me of mercy, I could not have believed it, being ſo confident of the contrary; and therefore I would tell thoſe that endeavoured to faſten counſel &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort upon me, it was but a caſting Pearls before Swine, and holy things to Dogs, which God forbids. And when ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral good women in <hi>Dublin</hi> did meet, to ſeek the Lord on my behalf; I thought ſometimes (eſpecially once in Miſtriſs <hi>Patients</hi> houſe) I ſmell'd Brimſtone
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93284:41"/> burning, and expected nothing but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; in the ſence of which I did tremble exceedingly, out of that deep horrour that was on my ſoul: but ſtill I got no ſenſible good in any of theſe meetings: and when I have ſeen the miſt aſcend ſometimes, that minded me of that Scripture where 'tis ſaid,<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.11.</note> 
               <hi>The ſmoak of their torment aſcendeth up for ever:</hi> And I have oft, as I have judged, ſeen <hi>Michaels</hi> meeting-houſe in <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blin,</hi> where we met to hear, full of ſmoak: all which I judged ſealed and confirmed my deſtruction.</p>
            <p>I do alſo remember when my dear Siſter <hi>Allen</hi> died at <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> I had little or no ſence of that with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like heavy ſtroaks of the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that time, upon divers other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ones; but did believe they were taken away for my ſake, becauſe they prayed for me, and that I was onely left to fill up the meaſure of my Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and therefore the Lord ſtopped many of their mouths by death, that they might not pray any more for me, but that I might be left to heap up wrath, and aggravate my miſery.</p>
            <p>I do likewiſe remember one morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93284:42"/> particularly at <hi>Dublin,</hi> when (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in bed, and called to riſe) I did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve verily I ſaw grievous flaſhes of lightning flie in my face, which put me in ſtrange honour: And alſo another morning ſeeing the Sun riſe in a miſty froſty morning very red, I had that Scripture come into my mind,<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joel</hi> 2.31.</note> of the <hi>Suns being turned into blood, before the great and notable day of the Lord;</hi> which I believed was then near, to my deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Another time being at a Chriſtian Friends (Miſtriſs <hi>Roe's</hi> houſe in <hi>Dublin</hi>) in the night ſeaſon I heard a voice (as I judged) over my head; a great voice, to which I hearkened, and was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by put into great horrour, thinking it to be the Devil, come to fetch me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and at laſt through anguiſh of ſoul was put into great trembling and ſweat; by reaſon of which, I ſpake to Miſtriſs <hi>Roe,</hi> who told me it was the people that lay over my head, that tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: But I did not believe her, but ſtill thought it was the Devil; and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards morning I heard a ratling of Chains (as I thought) which I judged to be the Devils haſting to fetch me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93284:42"/> with great rejoycing that they had got me; then I asked Miſtriſs <hi>Ree</hi> what that noiſe was; who told me, it was onely people opening Shop-win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows: but that ſatisfied not me, but I remained ſtill in an inexpreſſible horrour.</p>
            <p>I likewiſe remember the cauſe of my going to lie at Miſtriſs <hi>Roe's,</hi> was to get out of the room I lay in at my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, where I was ſenſible I had ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by wicked thoughts againſt God, as aforeſaid, from whoſe preſence alſo, as well as from that room, I would if I could have fled, it was ſo dreadful to me: But alas! my fears were not at all abated, but increaſed by going thither; it being the houſe where the Church met, and where was frequent ſpeaking and praying. At which I ſtill thought the Lord would come out, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt me, making me an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his juſtice in the ſight of all his people; whoſe often ſpeaking, to me, and praying for me, I did believe would aggravate my condemnation greatly: And when any of them ſpake of the promiſes to me, it was a great terrour to my ſoul, to ſee them caſt ſuch
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93284:43"/> Pearls before Swine, to whom they did not belong: by all which things, ſpoken to me, I was kept in a more certain looking for a fearful firy indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from the Lord, to deſtroy me; and my heart was the more enraged with an inveterate hatred (as I judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) againſt God and his people, by all the means uſed about me.</p>
            <p>And after all theſe things, coming to <hi>Waterford</hi> with my Brother <hi>Vernons</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and remaining there, I had not the like terrour as before; but was ſtupid, and more ſenceleſſe, being (as I judged) given up to a ſeared conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and heart, yet many times ſorely terrified with the like thoughts as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid: But was exceeding glad ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that I was forgotten in Prayer as I thought, and then did believe, it was revealed to them that prayed; ſo that they, knowing what I was, prayed not for me: for I had a great dread on my heart ſtill, about being prayed for, judging it haſtened my deſtruction, and that I ſhould by that means be made a fearful example of vengeance, to ſhew to others what I was; and thus it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued all the time I was at <hi>Waterford;</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:93284:43"/> no words ſpoken to me, or to the Lord for me, doing me any good as I could perceive; ſo that I ſtill concluded God could not lie, nor repent, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I muſt be damned; and that it was but in vain to attempt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>I alſo do remember when we came to Sea, to come for England, we were in a ſtorm: but I was in a ſenceleſſe, ſtupid condition, little minding my danger all the time.</p>
            <p>And after my Brother and Siſter <hi>Vernon</hi> landed at <hi>Milford,</hi> and the reſt of our Family with my ſelf and Brother <hi>Allen</hi> were come to Sea again, to go for <hi>Minhead,</hi> in a night and a day we had a very gracious paſſage given us, bringing us ſafe into the Bay of <hi>Minhead:</hi> And when there coming from the Ship-ſide, being all in the Boat, we had alſo an eminent delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; the Boat being in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be turn'd over by a Rope that was catched about the top of the Boats Maſt, juſt as we put off from the Ship, which, had it not been ſuddenly loos'd, had pull'd the Boat over, and buried us in the Sea: I was yet under all theſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93284:44"/> mercies with a ſenſeleſſe frame of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; onely I had ſome few thoughts of the infinite power of God in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding all things, and believed I was preſerved for the ſake of them I came with in the Ship: But coming into the Town of <hi>Minhead,</hi> and finding a hand of viſitation in that place, I concluded that was for my ſake, and that I was now come into the mouth of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; yet I was ſomething grieved to ſee the prophaneneſſe of the place and houſe where we were, which was as to ſin worſe then <hi>Ireland,</hi> whence we came; and then I thought of the terrible Judgements of God, againſt ſin, and ſinners, that lived under ſuch rich means of grace, as they here in <hi>England</hi> did. But leaving <hi>Minhead,</hi> and coming towards my Fathers houſe in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> I did not now doubt, (though I had ſpoken confidently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that the Lord would never let me ſee <hi>England,</hi> nor my Friends at home) but the Lord would bring us ſafe thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet remember not any thankfull ſenſe I had of the mercy received: but was thinking moſt part of the way as I came home, what a grief I ſhould be to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93284:44"/> my Friends and relations again; yet ſometimes a little ſenſe ſeemed to be on my heart, of the mercies aforeſaid, as I remember, and I did ſpeak of them to ſome in the Family after I came home: But ſoon after, I was in a dead ſtupid poſture as before, perceiving no good to me, either by ſpeakings or prayer, though uſed by ſome Friends then in the Family frequently; nor could I, nor durſt I pray; believing my Prayer was abominable: and therefore when my Siſter <hi>Vernons</hi> hour of Child-bearing drew near, I could not ſeek God f r her, but was unſenſible of her danger approaching: and after her delivery I was then in greater terror then before, thinking then that God would bring ſwift deſtruction upon me, as upon a Woman in travel, and I ſhould not eſcape.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now as to the Lords manner of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on my heart of late: It here followeth.</head>
               <p>ON the tenth day of the eleventh Moneth 1657. hearing a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon upon <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3.<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3</note> about per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93284:45"/> in a natural eſtate, being dead, it was of an afrightning conſideration to me, to think that Death and Hell was their Portion, and that Worms (as in the diſcourſe was mentioned) ſhould feed on ſuch, Even that Worm of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that ſhould gnaw continually; withal conſidering (as was then hinted) how loathſome a dead Creature is, fit onely to be fed on by all other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers: which I ſaw alſo to be my ſtate, and ſaw my loathſomneſſe in all my Actions, as alſo that without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God; which was ſet home upon my heart, and alſo that I was a ſubject of his wrath, which did abide upon me, &amp; ſo ſhould do to Eternity: Yet all this did not put me upon the uſe of any means to get out of my condition, in which I ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd, deſpairing of any way for my eſcape.</p>
               <p>After this, on the four and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of the eleventh Moneth, I heard again from another ſubject,<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 50.23. about Gods ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being ſhewed to thoſe that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their converſations aright: I had from this diſcourſe many fears on my
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93284:45"/> heart, eſpecially from that oft repeated Scripture,<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.155.</note> 
                  <hi>Salvation is far from the wicked, becauſe they keep not thy Law:</hi> Which was very terrible to me; and conſidering how abominable I was in God's ſight, by caſting his Laws behind my back; that Scripture was much on my heart,<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16.</note> 
                  <hi>What haſt thou to do to take my Words into thy mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt to be Reformed?</hi> Which made me believe he would deal with me, as is mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. of that <hi>Pſalm,</hi> even <hi>tear me in pieces, and none ſhould deliver;</hi> And becauſe I had rejected him as I had done, I ſhould ſuddenly be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and that without remedy: And hearing that paſſage mentioned out of <hi>Hannah's</hi> Song,<note n="(l)" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>The Enemies of the Lord ſhall be broken to pieces; out of Heaven will he thunder upon them:</hi> And I being (as I judged) one of his Enemies, it did ſorely terrify me.</p>
               <p>After this, on the ſix and twentieth day of the eleventh Moneth, in the night ſeaſon, my ſoul was much took up with thoughts about my ſad eſtate; and I was brought to conclude I was a Subject of the Lords diſpleaſure, and ſhould lie under the weight of his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93284:46"/> wrath to Eternity: And this ſorely terrified me, to think what a ſad thing it was to be caſt out of Gods ſight, and that for ever, and tormented with the Devil and his Angels, and this for ever, without any hopes of releaſe, or dram of comfort. This I thought to be a pit indeed, in which was no water, not the leaſt refreſhment; but unſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able miſeries, and that to Eternity; and it ſeemed ſtrange to me that I was out of Hell ſo long, conſidering what I had been, and done againſt the Lord; and alſo conſidering his infinite power, who could in a moment caſt me there, who had ſo provoked him as I had done.</p>
               <p>I came then to ſuppoſe this with my ſelf; were I now in Hell, and had but a poſſibility of eſcape, what means would I uſe to eſcape that horrible Pit? I alſo conſidered again, being once there, there was was no Redemption for ever: &amp; conſidering what great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger I was in dayly, of being caſt there, were the thrid of my life cut, which might ſuddenly be, and ſo I drop into Hell, paſt recovery.</p>
               <p>I being not yet there, and believing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93284:46"/> no Redemption from thence, when there; I came then to think, if yet there were any poſſibility of uſing means for my eſcape, I would try: for if I lie ſtill, I ſhall certainly periſh; and if I attempt the uſe of means, and miſſe obtaining what I ſeek for, I can but pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: and many very great ſinners have eſcaped through mercy; therefore I would try (and the Lord encouraged me from thoſe words of <hi>Eſther,</hi>
                  <note n="(m)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4.16.</note> 
                  <hi>I will go in to the King; if I periſh, I periſh:</hi> As alſo the reſolution of the Lepers,<note n="(n)" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.4.</note> In the Siege of Samaria) to uſe the means, though without hope of ſucceſſe. I being in ſuch a deplorable condition, was preſt to up and be doing, ſeeing the danger of lying ſtill; at laſt I came to reſolve to go hear at a Meeting in <hi>Sydbury:</hi> but I could not pray for a bleſſing, believing my Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was abominable to the Lord; and I had alſo (after I had reſolved) much ado to go, conſidering I was but an Hypocrite, and ſuch a one ſhould not ſtand before God; alſo conſidering what my thoughts againſt God were, and had been: I went with great fears on my heart, thinking (as formerly)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93284:47"/> the Lord would meet me in a way of rebuke, witneſſing againſt me: but then I thought alſo I could but periſh; and I had had ſuch thoughts of the Lords witneſſing againſt me formerly, which I had been miſtaken in, and ſo might be in theſe; and ſtill urged this to my heart, To abide in a way of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is nothing but death: onely in a way of righteouſneſſe is life; ſo that I had great fears each way, of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or ſtaying: But conſidering my nights reſolution, I fear'd if I went not I ſhould be found a Mocker of God; and ſo I went: but when I came there, my fears were renewed again, as to the Lords witneſſing againſt me: but I ſtrove againſt them, by calling to mind former miſtakes of this kind, and endeavoured to hear attentively; and after a while the Lord abated my fears aforeſaid, and afterwards almoſt clean removed them: The Subject ſpoken of at that time was ſloth; which having been ſo much my ſouls diſeaſe, I was very ſorely reproved by it, eſpecially afterward, when I ſeriouſly Meditated upon it: but yet I reſolved to wait in the uſe of means, bleſſing God (as I
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93284:47"/> was able) for what I heard this day; but yet remained in a very helpleſſe condition, having little or no hope of deliverance. This night afterwards, at prayers in the Family, I had my heart affected with ſome expreſſions uſed in Prayer about the dreadfulneſſe of Chriſts appearing to his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for their rejecting him in his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to them.</p>
               <p>On the ſeven and twentieth day at night, I had many fears on my heart, in ſo much that I was afraid to ſtay in any room; and would, if I could, have fled from the preſence of God, it was ſo terrible to me. And about twelve of the Clock at night I came into my Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Vernons</hi> Chamber; but horrour ſo ſeized on me in all places, as I was forced once this night to go and cry to the Lord for mercy: but whilſt I was in my Siſters Chamber, I heard one walking in another room near, which made me afraid to go back again, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving it was the Devil; but after un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding it to be one of the Maids that was up, I return'd again then into the Chamber ſomewhat freed from my fears, and went to bed; but having got
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93284:48"/> cold with being up, I found my ſelf much diſtempered, both in my body and head.</p>
               <p>And kept my Bed the next day till night: Then I got up for refreſhment for a while, but remember not any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable paſſage farther this night; but had many ſad grieving thoughts for my rejecting Chriſt, which were often on my heart this day; and alſo I had a little view of the excellency of Chriſt, and ſpake to ſome in the Family of it in theſe words, <hi>His Fruit is better then Life;</hi> which I thought aggravated my Iniquity in rejecting him, beſides whom there is not another that can ſave; and that I ſhould reject him, it ſorely afflicted me: But I had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that day theſe words, <hi>He waits to be gratious;</hi> which ſomewhat incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and revived me to wait: And it grieved me exceedingly for my reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting him, his word and counſel, who ſhall be the deſire of Nations; yea that <hi>Tree of Life, whoſe Leaves are for the healing of Nations, with whom is Riches and Honour; yea dureable Riches and Righteouſneſſe:</hi> All theſe repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſt to me, heightened my ſin,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93284:48"/> and grief for my rejecting him: And even broke my heart in the ſence of it moſt part of this day.</p>
               <p>On the eight and twentieth day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, I heard again in the Family from the 28. Chapter of the <hi>Proverbs;</hi> the firſt Verſe of which Chapter took hold on me, as ſuch a one as there is mentioned, fleeing from the Lord as from my purſuer, which I have many a time done: but in that diſcourſe it was ſhewn, that deſpair is the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to Hell; which much dwell'd with me in the night ſeaſon: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakening in the night, and hearing the wind blow hard, it ſorely terrifyed me; being the voice (as I thought) of God my terrible Judge, conſidering him as a conſuming fire againſt all Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent Rejectors of him, of which number I was one; and looking on him as a God of infinite power, able to caſt me into Hell in a moment: and I remaining a Subject of his wrath, in a ſtate of unbelief, it made me fear ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly: but withal conſidering, that ſtill to remain in this condition, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but deſtruction could be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; as alſo that there was no flying
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93284:49"/> from his preſence, before whom all places, perſons, and things are open and bare, and from whom nothing can be hid; Hell and deſtruction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing open, and known to him, how much more the hearts of the Sons of Men? I hence concluded my condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be exceeding ſad; and then conſidering what a Rebel I had been, ſetting at nought his counſels, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting his Laws behind my back; yea deſpiſing, hating, and contemning him, it made me afraid to go to him: But ſeeing no way to go from him, and my ſelf in this deſperate condition, I muſt needs be ruin'd by him, if I came not unto him. He at laſt led me to this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of flying to him, begging mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy at his hands, for the ſake of Chriſt, as one who ſaw my ſelf in the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to Hell; and knowing that his right hand would eaſily find out all his Adverſaries that had hated and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him.</p>
               <p>So that there would be no eſcaping, but by flying to Chriſt; there being <hi>NO OTHER NAME UNDER HEAVEN GIVEN FOR SAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VATION, UNTO POOR
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93284:49"/> SINNERS, BUT THIS ONELY.</hi> And ſo out of this great depth I was inabled to look towards his holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, crying to him for mercy, without which I ſaw I was undone for ever; ſo I continued crying to him, and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with my own ſoul, to hope that the Lord would for Chriſts ſake ſhew mercy to me, becauſe he had ſhewed mercy to very vile ſinners; though I knew none ſo vile as I, being the chief of ſinners, having long deſpiſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected that mercy that then I ſought; yet ſeeing what a woefull condition I ſhould for ever be in without it, I cryed to him for it; and then had ſome Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations given in, of the way of God's ſhewing mercy, conſidering how he had found out a way for mercy and truth to meet together in Chriſt, for the Salvation of poor ſinners, yea the chief of ſinners: and the Lord brought at that time ſome paſſages to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, that I had heard about the City of refuge, provided in the time of the Law; which was then minded typed out Chriſt, as the City of refuge prepared of God for poor purſued ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to flie unto from that wrath that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93284:50"/> all would be elſe concluded under to Eternity: And the Lord alſo was gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly pleaſed to enable me, to have recourſe to Chriſt, as the onely refuge left for my poor ſoul; begging hard for mercy upon his account, and the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what he had done and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ſuch poor ſinners as I was; and I was helpt alſo to conſider the large extent of his mercy to the vileſt of ſinners; and ſuddenly after, I was gratiouſly helpt to hope in his mercy, and ſupported and incouraged from that good word (then brought with power upon my ſoul)<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 3.7.</note> 
                  <hi>He that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me, I will in no wiſe caſt out;</hi> which did greatly ſupport me in good hopes of mercy from him; and after that, this other good word was brought in with great power upon my heart,<note n="(q)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is able to ſave to the uttermoſt, all that come unto God by him, ſeeing he ever lives to make interceſſion for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This alſo added much to the ground of my hope in his mercy, that though I had been ſuch a Rebel, and great tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor, as I had been; yet he having ſaid he would in no wiſe caſt out any that came to him, &amp; was able to ſave to the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93284:50"/> uttermoſt; it much upheld and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted my ſoul in looking towards him.</p>
               <p>Another Scripture brought in at the ſame time to my heart, was,<note n="(r)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſai.</hi> 43.12, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>I am God, and beſides me there is no Savior; I will work, and none ſhall let it;</hi> whence I was inabled to believe that he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do all things by the word of his power, and to break through all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions that ſtand in his way; that he was able to break down every ſtrong hold, and ſubject every high thought to his obedience. I then had Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the heights, and depths; lengths, and bredths, of that infinite mercy that was in Jeſus Chriſt: and the Lord by ſuch Meditations on his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly word, did greatly incourage, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and raiſe up my poor, weak, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſoul, very often (and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully) repeating theſe Scriptures, laſt mentioned, over and over to my poor ſoul: and now was my ſoul greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed in hopes of his mercy to me; but a little after, the ſame night,<note place="margin">Her firſt Aſſault af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter comfort received.</note> 
                  <hi>I was ſorely aſſaulted again, to call in queſtion all the hopes I had of mercy from the Lord:</hi> in the ſenſe of which, I was made to cry, yea roar out in bitter diſtreſs to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93284:51"/> the Lord, ſtriving not to let go my hold, but to call to mind what he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpoken: Namely, <hi>That thoſe that come to him, he will in no wiſe caſt out;</hi> together with the reſt of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures before mentioned, given in at firſt for my incouragement: and the Lord again, in this ſore conflict, brought in all thoſe Scriptures afreſh upon my heart, and ſo relieved me gratiouſly at this time alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Her ſecond Aſſault.</note>But yet the tempter continued his aſſaults; tempting me <hi>yet to caſt off my confidence in the Lord, as alſo to bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheme God:</hi> But the Lord upheld me, by putting and keeping under his everlaſting Armes; By which I was ſtayed upon him, truſting in him, and was not left to the will of mine Enemy: but was inabled ſtill to hope in his mercy, and hang upon that word of his promiſe, <hi>He that cometh to me, I will in no wiſe caſt out:</hi> &amp; then the Lord was pleaſed eminently to proclaim his name unto my ſoul: <hi>The Lord, the Lord God, pardoning iniquity, tranſgreſſion, and ſin.</hi> And thus I was inabled (through his infinite mercy, and by his Almighty Power) to ſtay my ſelf upon him, by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93284:51"/> hoping ſtill in his mercy, for ever bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be his name. And the ſame Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were kept on my heart all the firſt day of the week following, with great life and power, ſuccouring me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Satans temptations, that this day alſo I was aſſaulted with, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to caſt away my confidence as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, from thoughts of what I had been, and done againſt Chriſt: but the Lord inabled me to withſtand that temptation alſo by his good word, in which he had cauſed me to truſt: namely, <hi>He that comes to me, I will in no wiſe caſt out:</hi> As alſo that he <hi>would work, and none ſhould let:</hi> So that I went to God (through Chriſt) deſiring he would inable my ſoul to follow hard after him: begging in order thereto, that he would uphold me, cauſing my ſoul to experience the truth of his word, that it doth and ſhall indure for ever: that I might be able from experience to witneſs to it, as <hi>ſo enduring, by his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver failing, nor forſaking me.</hi> But that I might know him <hi>as a God that keeps Covenant and mercy for ever with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> which laſt words were this day made ſweet to my Meditation.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:93284:52"/>
               <p>Alſo this day hearing in the Family from <hi>Pſalm</hi> 63.8. <hi>My ſoul followeth hard after thee, thy right hand upholds me;</hi> I was able to ſay, I had experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>right hand upholdings:</hi> and my ſoul was now taught to beg earneſtly for a heart inabled to follow hard after him, that hath ſo upheld, that I might follow him reſolutely, patiently, expectingly, and conſtantly, as was then minded in that Sermon. I alſo begged I might be kept low in my own eyes, under the receipt of mercy, looking on the Lord Jeſus, as the Spring and Fountain of all in me, and to me, owning the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his grace to me.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially conſidering what a Rebel I had been againſt him, and how juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he might have caſt me off for ever, had it not pleaſed him to advance rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of grace to me, a poor vile undone Creature, who deſires his name alone may have all the glory; and ſince he hath ſhewed this mercy to me, my ſouls great fears are, leſt I ſhould ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to my ſelf: But I deſire I may for ever be kept in the ſence of my own unworthineſſe of the leaſt mercy from him, upon any other account then
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93284:52"/> the good pleaſure of his own will, made known in and by Chriſt, to poor ſinners.<note place="margin">Her third Aſſault.</note> 
                  <hi>Yet this night I was aſſaulted again with many blaſphemous thoughts darted into my ſoul, againſt God, by the tempter, cauſing fears and faintings ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times:</hi> Yet I ſtrove againſt them, crying to the Lord for help, to reſiſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, deſiring he would alſo work ſuch a holy fear in my heart, as I might never more diſhonour him, who had ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly helpt me out of ſuch depths, to look towards him, and to hope in his mercy, who was pleaſed this night a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain very gratiouſly to ſupport me with the ſame promiſes at firſt given in, and now again afreſh, as it were repeated, and confirm'd further to my ſoul. And by theſe he now alſo upheld me againſt departing from him; &amp; after great ſtriving and ſtrugling to keep my hold on the promiſes, I had alſo a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious view of the love of God given in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ſoul, though the vileſt of ſinners, which did greatly refreſh me, enabling me (more fully) to believe in him: and this Scripture<note n="(s)" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.</note> was much ſet upon my heart, <hi>That he hath made him to be ſin for us, who knew no ſin, that we might be made
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93284:53"/> the Righteouſneſſe of God in him:</hi> As alſo that,<note n="(t)" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</note> 
                  <hi>He is made unto us of God, Wiſdome, Righteouſneſſe, Sanctification, and Redemption:</hi> So that I was inabled now to ſee my ſelf juſtified, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit in the ſight of God, through Chriſt, from all my iniquity, which was now hid, and covered; and God in Chriſt well pleaſed with me, upon the account of his righteouſneſſe onely; ſo that I was (being thus refreſhed) inabled to admire his grace to ſuch a poor worthleſſe Creature as I was; and I had my ſoul then much enlarged in deſires after him, that I might be kept in time to come, from diſhonouring him by unbelief, or any other way, who had been ſo gratious, yea rich in mercy to one ſo unworthy; yea even unto me, who had been ſuch a bitter Enemy unto him. Oh, this did much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his love to my ſoul, cauſing me the more to admire it, by reflecting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what I had been, and what I had done againſt him.</p>
               <p>On the ſecond day of the week I was alſo carried on for the moſt part, in a holy Admiration of his kindneſſe to me: Deſiring, I might ſtill be inabled
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93284:53"/> to depend on him, and his grace ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted through Chriſt Jeſus to me; and might be inabled ſtill to preſs hard after him, from the manifeſtation of his love through Chriſt to my ſoul: as alſo that I might be inabled to give glory to God by believing; and that I might never more by an evil heart of unbelief, depart, or fly from the Lord, or diſhonour him by hearkning to the voice of the tempter; but might hear and know his voice, and follow him, and no more the voice of ſtrangers, but onely him, who had been ſo abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly gratious to ſuch an unworthy Creature, who never deſerved the leaſt dram of his grace or mercy, but the greateſt of his wrath and fury to be poured out upon me: And that ſuch a ſence of my undone condition, and his right-hand-help extended to me in it, might teach me for ever to aſcribe grace &amp; glory to his name, &amp; that only: it alſo was now my ſouls Requeſt that I might be inbled to return thanks in truth to him by my unfeigned obedience to all his commands, alſo by ſearching af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the more clear knowledge of his will, in any thing wherein I might yet
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93284:54"/> be dark, or ignorant; deſiring that I might neither deſpiſe, neglect, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn any of his Commands, though reckoned ſmall or contemptible in the eye of the world: but that, what ever his mind is, I ſhould do; I might be inabled to honour him therein, freely and ſincerely, though never ſo weakly, and might never willingly neglect any Command of his: but might with full purpoſe of heart cleave to him, and his wayes, no more ſinfully to depart from them, whatever I may be expoſed to, &amp; that the truth and integrity of my heart might even appear to the glory of God, in my being ſound a <hi>follower of thoſe, who through faith and patience inherit the promiſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond day of the week at night, I had a more large view of the Lords love, and more refreſhings then I had before. And I was now inabled to ſee that all ſorts of good was laid up for me in Chriſt, both for ſoul and body, from that Scripture,<note n="(u)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 1.19.</note> 
                  <hi>For it pleaſed the Father that in him ſhould all fulneſſe dwell:</hi> And this fulneſſe I ſaw was laid up in him for all believers: and I was made to ſee that all that good contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93284:54"/> in any of the promiſes, it was in him and by him given out to believers, through the promiſes; and that it ſhould be enjoyed by believers in him, with unſpeakable ſafety and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he never failing any that truſt in him: for he hath ſaid, <hi>None that truſt in him ſhallbe deſolate, nor ſhould any be able to pluck them out of his hand, nor out of his Fathers hand, who is greater then he.</hi> Theſe with many other pretious promiſes did then flow in abundantly to my ſoul, carrying me out of my ſelf by faith to him, ſo that I was inabled to reſign up my ſelf, and commit the keeping of my ſoul, and all that I have, and am, to him whom I had found thus faithful, (and alſo able) to keep what was committed to him, and to preſent me before his Father, without ſpot, and blameleſſe, at that great day of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing: And I was now made willing to be at his diſpoſe, and to be govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him; deſiring that he onely might have Dominion in my ſoul; and I be inabled by him to follow him whitherſoever he goes, and into what condition ſoever he would carry me: according to that Character given of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93284:55"/> his redeemed ones,<note n="(w)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe are they which follow the Lamb, whitherſoever he goeth:</hi> Which Scripture was at that time born in, with great weight on my ſoul, making me earneſtly beg, That I might be inabled to deny my ſelf, and take up his Croſſe, and follow him; depending on him for whatever I might ſtand in need of, being inabled (through grace) to believe, that all the promiſes are in him yea, and Amen: Yea the good of every of them laid up in him, more fully then in them. And afterwards I was inabled to reſign up my ſelf to him, as before expreſſed; and then did the promiſes plentifully flow into my ſoul.</p>
               <p>As firſt, That I ſhould<note n="(x)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.17.</note> be <hi>ſaved with an everlaſting Salvation,</hi> and <hi>ſhould not be aſhamed world without end; and that none ſhould be able to pluck any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever out of Chriſt's hand:</hi> So that I was inabled to ſay,<note n="(y)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa</hi> 45.24, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>In him have I righteouſneſſe, and ſtrength: And in him ſhall all the Seed of Iſrael be juſtified, and ſhall glory:</hi> And that promiſe alſo,<note n="(z)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 84.11.</note> 
                  <hi>He will be a Sun, and aſhield; yea grace and glory will he give, and no good thing will he withhold,</hi> &amp;c. And I was inabled to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93284:55"/> believe, <hi>That I ſhould be kept by the mighty Power of God, through Faith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Salvation.</hi> Theſe, with many more pretious promiſes, with the comforts of them, in a far larger meaſure then I can now relate, were given in to me. I had alſo particular promiſes for gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and leading given in to my ſoul: as that,<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 7.17.</note> 
                  <hi>If any man will do my will, he ſhall know of the Doctrine, whether it be of God, or not:</hi> And<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 32.8.</note> 
                  <hi>I will guide them with mine eye;</hi> and<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Then ſhall ye know, if you follow on to know the Lord:</hi> And that alſo<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.20.</note> 
                  <hi>I lead in the way of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in the midſt of the paths of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I had many promiſes alſo, as to proviſion, as<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 36.8.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſhall be abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied with the fatneſſe of thy houſe; and ſhall drink of the Rivers of thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures:</hi> And alſo that<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 25.6.</note> 
                  <hi>In this Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain will the Lord make a Feast of fat things; a Feast of Wine on the lees well refined.</hi> And I was inabled now to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <hi>My life was hid with Chriſt in God: and that becauſe he lived, I ſhould live al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; and that he was come, that we might have life, and might have it more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly; as alſo that he ever liveth to make
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:93284:56"/> interceſſion for us: and that he was come into the world, that whoſoever believes in him, ſhould not abide in darkneſſe: and that he would be a Sun as well as a ſhield; yea he would give grace, and glory, and no good thing will he withhold,</hi> &amp;c. And in contemplation on theſe promiſes, and the grace contain'd in them, &amp; the dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of them, (which I was aſſured ſhould not fail in one tittle to be made good) I was kept up the third day of the week, in a holy Admiration of my ſoul, enjoying ſweet refreſhment for the moſt part, from the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the infinite goodneſſe of God, ſet off, and exceedingly heightened to my ſoul, by the conſideration of that abounding evil in me, to whom all this rich mercy had been ſhewed: And in this frame for the moſt part, both the fourth day of the week, and the night alſo, and likewiſe on the fifth day of the week, it was much the ſame with me.</p>
               <p>But on the fifth day at night again, the Enemy <hi>aſſaulted,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Her fourth Aſſault from Satan.</note> and conflicted very ſore with me, <hi>To make me look on all the grace received, as a poor and low thing:</hi> And I was alſo tempted to <hi>fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and blaſphemous thoughts againſt God:</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:93284:56"/> This was before I went to lie down to take my reſt; which ſtorm cauſed me to fly to my refuge, the Lord Jeſus, for help in this needful time: Saying unto him in my ſoul, Becauſe thou haſt been my refuge, therefore under the ſhadow of thy Wings will I put my truſt. I then alſo pleaded the Lord's good word, in which he had cauſed me to hope: Namely, <hi>That thoſe that came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, he would in no wiſe caſt out; and that he had ſaid, he would never leave, nor forſake me, nor would turn away from me, or let my ſoul depart from him:</hi> All which I pleaded with him; earneſtly begging from him ſtrength, to reſiſt the Enemies temptations, that I might not diſhonour the Lord by hearkning or conſenting to any of his temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or ſuggeſtions. I alſo pleaded with him his good word, of treading down Satan under foot ſhortly; and his making good that word, that the <hi>Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt his Saints:</hi> This being his word which he hath ſaid ſhould endure for ever, in which my ſoul hath truſted: Yet ſtill theſe <hi>Aſſaults were continued,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aſſaults continued.</note> to cauſe me to caſt off my hope: but the Lord
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:93284:57"/> ſuccoured and upheld me, and at laſt through mercy vanquiſhed my Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies for me; alſo giving me ſuch a wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling frame of Spirit, during the conflict, that I could not let him go, till he had bleſs'd me, by making good the word I pleaded with him, in many reſpects to my poor ſoul.</p>
               <p>For ever bleſſed be his Name, for ſuch Riches of grace as he came in to my ſoul with. In this conflict alſo, making me witneſſe to the truth of his word, that he is indeed a God that keeps covenant and mercy, and that for ever, with ſuch as fear him. And after I had been thus conflicting, I was enabled to read in his word comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, without moleſtation any more this night; and had my heart much refreſh'd, in beholding the Lord's faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to me in my hour of tryal; which made my ſoul more firmly reſt upon him, &amp; truſt in him, ſeeing he had not ſuffered his faithfulneſſe to fail, nor altered the thing gone out of his mouth, nor removed, nor took away his loving kindneſſe from me. And ſo I lay down to reſt, having been thus eminently refreſh'd, and ſupported by
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:93284:57"/> the Lord: I had alſo my ſleep made ſweet to me; and when I awoke in the night ſeaſon, it was with this Scripture,<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>He will reſt in his love, he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce over thee with ſinging:</hi> As alſo this Scripture, <hi>He will never leave thee, nor forſake thee:</hi> Then alſo had I a <hi>moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious view of the eternal love of God to my ſoul,</hi> letting me ſee the reaſon, why I was not (long ſince) conſumed; which was, becauſe <hi>he had made an everlaſting Covenant on my behalf, in Chriſt Jeſus my Lord, in all things well ordered and ſure, and that he was ever mindful of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi> Oh! this was ſweet, and this (even this) was the reaſon I was not caſt off in my rebellions; becauſe <hi>he hath loved me with an everlaſting love, therefore with loving kindneſſe hath he drawn me, and that for his own name ſake he deferr'd his anger: that he cut me not off, nor did he retain his anger for ever, becauſe mercy pleaſed him, &amp; he delighted to be gratious.</hi> The coming in of theſe did even ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my ſoul, as with Marrow, in the thoughts of his <hi>infinite, Eternal, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable love:</hi> Which I ſaw indeed was the reaſon of my not being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, <hi>becauſe he is God, and changeth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93284:58"/> not:</hi> and in his protection, and infinite love, and mercy, my ſoul did now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, ſeeing its ſafety under the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of his Wings, believing I ſhould for ever be kept by him, and he would <hi>uphold me with the right hand of his righteouſneſſe, and would never fail, nor forſake me; but would reſt in his love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſixth day I was kept up much in the ſenſe of love, peace, and joy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded me the night before from God my gratious Father; my ſoul ſtill truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his word, with which he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed and ſupported me: And ſtill I was inabled to believe, to my great comfort, <hi>That his word ſhould endure for ever:</hi> from which word, laſt mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I have been inabled to plead with God, in my conflicts, after this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, thou haſt promiſed, that they that come to thee, thou wilt in no wiſe caſt out; and if ſo, then canſt thou not turn away from doing thy people good; but wilt according to thy good word, ſprinkle them with clean water, and from all their idols and Iniquities thou wilt cleanſe them; yea thou wilt take away the ſtony heart, and give them hearts of Fleſh, with thy Laws writen in them, and thy fear put ſo into
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:93284:58"/> their inward parts, as they ſhall not depart from thee: this Lord is thy word, in which thou haſt cauſed my ſoul to truſt.</hi> Thus have I been inabled to plead his new Covenant-mercy to my ſouls ſupport, and upholding in ſtraits; bleſſed be his name.</p>
               <p>This night I had a good nights reſt, and was much refreſh'd, on the ſeventh day in the morning, with thoughts much enlarged upon the <hi>great good laid up by the Lord, for them that fear him:</hi> and had many promiſes preſented a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh to my ſoul, for future encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo that I was inabled (through his grace) to admire his infinite love in Jeſus Chriſt, and to have my ſoul fully ſatisfied in that onely, and to teſtifie my ſatisfaction therein, by deſiring and endeavouring for ever to be, to the praiſe of his rich grace made known to me, by being dedicated wholly to his ſervice; <hi>Whoſe workmanſhip I am, being created in Chriſt Jeſus to good works, to the end we ſhould walk in them:</hi> Giving glory and honour to Chriſt, <hi>Who alone is worthy to receive it from us, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed us out of all kindreds and tongues, &amp;c. and having waſh'd us in his own
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:93284:59"/> Blood, and made us Kings and Prieſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God the Father; and we ſhall Reign for evermore.</hi> I alſo conſidered it was for this end, that he gave himſelf to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem us, that we might be a peculiar people to himſelf, zealous of good works: And to this end I deſired, <hi>My ſoul might have Fellowſhip with him in his death, ſufferings, and reſurrection, being made conformable to him in his death, and raiſed up, and brought forth by the power of his Spirit, in the Fellowſhip of his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Fifth Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault from Satan.</note>But this ſeventh day at night I was again <hi>aſſaulted with blaſphemous thoughts,</hi> and tempted <hi>to ſlighty and low thoughts af all his grace and love made known to me:</hi> And was ſeized with much fear (as I am uſually in all theſe conflicts) leſt I ſhould be overcome, and diſhonour God by hearkning, &amp; conſenting to the ſuggeſtions of his and my Enemy: But the Lord this night alſo was not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me, but did uphold me in wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon him; inabling me to ſeek to him, &amp; reſt upon him, his word in which he had cauſed my ſoul to truſt. And in this way he came in to me, manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf exceeding gratious to my
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:93284:59"/> relief, and helped me to vanquiſh thoſe temptations; giving me ſtrength againſt them, and inabling me to ſpeak to his praiſe, what he had done for my ſoul, to the end it might be recorded: yet when I came this night to ſpeak of theſe things, that ſo they might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, I was much afraid I ſhould not be able, being much ſtraitened, and ſhut up: but the Lord opened my heart, and my mouth ſpake (through his aſſiſtance) to his praiſe.</p>
               <p>The ſeventh day at night I went to bed late; and when I awaked in the morning, the Lord made my Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of him to be ſweet to me, cauſing me much ſtill to rejoyce in the love of God my Saviour. My firſt Meditation being of his infinite love and wiſdom, in finding out <hi>a way for recovering and reconciling poor, loſt, fallen man to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and ſuch a way wherein mercy and truth might meet together, righteouſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe and peace might k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe each other.</hi> And this Scripture was much on my heart,<note n="g" place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9.</note> 
                  <hi>If we confeſſe our ſins, he is faithful and juſt to forgive us our ſins.</hi> And that was ſweet, to ſee it was not onely mercy, but faithfulneſſe, and juſtice, to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:93284:60"/> forgive ſins unto poor penitent ſinners for the ſake of Chriſt, The Mediator between God and man, in whom God ſaw himſelf and Juſtice fully ſatisfied; and the poor believer might ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf fully acquitted, as if he had not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: And all this I ſaw as the Fruit of Chriſts death and reſurrection, he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in our ſtead fully diſcharged our debts, which we elſe could never have ſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fied; by whom onely we receive the Atonement. I had alſo a far more pretious and inlarged diſcovery of theſe things, then I am now able to mention, with many choice Scriptures brought to my mind, as to this head: Namely,<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 68.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt aſcended on high: Thou haſt led captivity captive: Thou haſt received gifts for men, yea for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious alſo, that the Lord God might dwell among them: and that by Chriſt all hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writings that were againſt us, were taken out of the way, and nailed to his Croſs, who hath ſpoiled principalities and Powers, triumphing over them openly:</hi> And that by him <hi>the ſting of death, and ſtrength of the Law were taken away:</hi> According to his good word:<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55, 56, 57.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh Death, I will be thy death: O Grave, I will be thy deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93284:60"/> The ſting of death is ſin; and the ſtrength of ſin is the Law: But thanks be to God, who giveth us the Victory through our Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſus Chriſt.</hi> Oh! theſe Scriptures were <hi>FOOD AND STRENGTH</hi> to my ſoul: At this time alſo that Scripture was given in,<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Titus</hi> 3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>After the kindneſſe and love of God our Saviour towards man appeared; not by works of righteouſneſſe, which we have done: but according to his mercy he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us, by the waſhing of regeneration, and renewing of the holy Ghoſt, which he ſhed on us abundantly through Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour:</hi> So that I ſaw our Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was the Fruit of his purchaſe for us, and Free-gift to us; it being one great end in his laying down his life, that he might redeem &amp; purifie to himſelf a peculiar people, zealous of good works. I had many Meditations alſo,<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> about the Lords paſſing by us, when we lay polluted in our blood, and caſt out to the loathing of our perſons, in the day we were born, that then he ſhould ſay to us, Live; and that this ſhould be the time of love, and ſpreading his skirt over us: as alſo to conſider, that the promiſe of Chriſt,<note n="(m)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen</hi> 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>(And I will
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:93284:61"/> put enmity between thee and the woman, and between thy ſeed and her ſeed: It ſhall bruiſe thy head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heel)</hi> was given to fallen man, in that nick of time of the greateſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which he had brought on himſelf and poſterity.</p>
               <p>I had then alſo many Meditations of God's power, by which he is able <hi>to keep us through faith unto Salvation;</hi> with many promiſes given in to that purpoſe, as, that<note n="(n)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 34.22.</note> 
                  <hi>none that truſt in him ſhall be deſolate:</hi> As alſo that was made ſweet to my ſoul:<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 33.16, 17.</note> namely, <hi>His place of defence ſhall be the munition of Rocks: bread ſhall be given him, and his Waters ſhall be ſure; and thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty, and behold the Land that is very far off.</hi> Theſe were MEAT TO ME INDEED at that time, Thus to conſider the ſafety of believers as founded upon the Rock of ages.</p>
               <p>And alſo that Scripture,<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord thou wilt ordain peace for us, for thou alſo haſt wrought all our works in us:</hi> and likewiſe that,<note n="(q)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.3.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord will not ſuffer the ſoul of the righteous to famiſh: but he caſts away the ſubſtance of the wicked:</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:93284:61"/> And<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.29.</note> 
                  <hi>the way of the Lord is ſtrength to the upright; but deſtruction ſhall be to the workers of Iniquity:</hi> And that,<note n="s" place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</note> 
                  <hi>Peace I leave with you; my peace Is give unto you, not as the world giveth give I unto you: Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid:</hi> And<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 14.13.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe I live, you ſhall live alſo:</hi> And<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 5.19.</note> 
                  <hi>he ſhall deliver thee in ſix troubles, yea in ſeven, there ſhall no evil touch thee:</hi> And<note n="w" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.11.</note> 
                  <hi>their ſouls ſhall be as a watered Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, that God hath bleſſed:</hi> And<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 27.3.</note> 
                  <hi>I the Lord do keep it; I will water it every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, leſt any hurt it: I will keep it night and day.</hi> With theſe promiſes was my ſoul refreſh'd greatly this night; and from hence was I led to meditate on the great care, love, and tender pity of the Lord, towards his poor people, in making ſo many pretious promiſes for ſupport and ſuccour for his poor Saints: which made me even (with Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) admire his grace herein: and then was that good word brought in ſweetly refreſhing me,<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 41.17.</note> 
                  <hi>When the poor and needy ſeek water, and there is none, and their tongue faileth for thirſt, I the Lord will hear them; I the God of Iſrael will not forſake them.</hi> I then cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:93284:62"/> to mind how largely my ſoul had experienc'd the truth of that word, that even when I was ready to fail and ſink, &amp; my ſoul even ſcorcht up with <hi>the heat of the wrath of the Lord,</hi> without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, yea without a heart to ſeek it; he made good this to me: <hi>For ever bleſſed be his name, and the Riches of his grace, made known in Chriſt to my ſoul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now did the Lord bring my ſoul to this <hi>Well of conſolation, and made me drink abundantly of the River of his pleaſures ſtreaming out in theſe promiſes:</hi> and gave me Fruit indeed from the Tree of Life; feeding me from that word alſo<note n="(z)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55.3.</note> 
                  <hi>I will make an everlaſting Covenant with you, even the ſure mercies of David:</hi> Which I ſaw were ſure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as laid no in Chriſt for believers. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en in him <hi>whom God hath exalted as a Prince and a Saviour, to give repentance unto Iſrael, for remiſſion of ſins: who him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was tempted, that he might be able to ſuccour thoſe that are tempted;</hi> Whom God hath raiſed from the dead, that our li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and hope might be in him, who hath called poor and weary ſouls to come to him for reſt, and hath made me amongſt others <hi>largely experience</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:93284:62"/> the truth of that word, in cauſing my ſoul to <hi>find reſt onely in him,</hi> after a long and ſore travail, and wearyſome jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Yet again, this firſt day of the week I was <hi>aſſaulted</hi> in hearing the word Preached,<note place="margin">Her ſixth Aſſault from Satan.</note> 
                  <hi>with many filthy ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions caſt in, to cauſe me to undervalue the grace of God made known:</hi> And this was both forenoon, and afternoon: but yet I was gratiouſly helpt to ſtrive againſt them; and to cry out to the Lord for help and aſſiſtance, to reſiſt the wicked one; begging, The Lord would not ſuffer me to diſhonour his holy name, by conſenting to the temptors ſuggeſtions: and then I call'd to mind that word, wherein he had cauſed me to truſt: Namely,<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.</note> 
                  <hi>That he vvould never leave me, nor forſake me: but vvould put his fear ſo in my heart, as I ſhould not depart from him; neither ſhould the Gates of Hell prevail againſt me:</hi> And thus by flying to him as my Sanctuary, I was inabled to reſiſt, and overcome my Enemies, who elſe had been too hard for me.</p>
               <p>I had alſo this day,<note place="margin">Her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault from Satan.</note> while I was hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſome ſad conſiderations about <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling avvay, after grace received;</hi> which
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93284:63"/> made my ſoul to tremble in the thoughts of it, to think how diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able that would be to the name of God: but I had ſome hopes in his word, which ſupported and ſtrenghthened me againſt theſe fears: Namely, That the <hi>Lord vvould keep me by his Povver through faith unto Salvation;</hi> and would alſo according to his Covenant <hi>put his fear in my heart, that I ſhould not (at leaſt utterly) depart from him:</hi> but yet had many fears, that if he ſhould but eclipſe his love to my ſoul, that might alſo be to the diſhonour of his name, and an occaſion of ſtumbling to others; which alſo made my ſoul full of fears in the thoughts of it. But this ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what flay'd me, that he, who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun a good work, will finiſh it, and will be careful of his own glory, which in my ſouls upholding is ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">She is help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what ſhe owed unto the Lord for all his mercy.</note>I was after theſe converſings with the Lord, and ſweet Communion with him, led to conſider what all this calls for at my hand, and was cauſed to deſire to teſtifie my love to Jeſus Chriſt, in wayes of obedience to all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, who had ſo plentifully manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93284:63"/> his love to my ſoul: and at laſt was led to ſome Meditations about Baptiſm, looking upon it as a duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon all believers, whereby they did evidence their love to Chriſt, in obedience to his Commands. But withal, I had ſome fears on my heart, about my being carried on in that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which I ſee to be ſo contemn'd and deſpiſed: but did judge, theſe were but the tempters ſuggeſtions; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did earneſtly deſire of the Lord, that he would inable me to evidence my ſincerity to him, by following him in his moſt deſpiſed paths; and that I might not dare to neglect any duty he calls for at my hands: then alſo was I brought to mind that Scripture,<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29.</note> 
                  <hi>To you it's given not onely to believe, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to ſuffer for his ſake:</hi> And that he onely could give this gift, which was a great honour to be conferr'd upon his poor Saints, to be counted worthy to ſuffer for his name; and I begg'd, It might ever be ſo accounted by me: that Scripture alſo I had on my mind,<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.37.</note> 
                  <hi>He that loveth Father or Mother more then me, is not worthy of me:</hi> As likewiſe<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.29.</note> 
                  <hi>No man that hath left houſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:93284:64"/> or Brethren, or Siſters, or Father, or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or Wife, or Children, or Lands for my ſake, and the Goſpels, but he ſhall receive an hundred fold now in this time; houſes, and Brethren, and Siſters, and Mothers, and Children, and Lands, with perſecution, and in the world to come, life Eternal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now by a hundred fold in this life, I underſtood to be in peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that would be more then all the comforts I could forſake for it; Beſides in the world to come life everlaſting: And that Scripture alſo I had,<note n="(e)" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>For our Light afflictions, which are but for a moment, do work for us a far more exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Eternal weight of glory, whileſt we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at thoſe things that are not ſeen: for the things that are ſeen, are temporal; but thoſe that are not ſeen, are Eternal:</hi> I alſo minded, <hi>Moſes</hi> his eying the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of reward, made him deſpiſe the pleaſures of <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> Court; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe what the Saints mentioned,<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</note> had endured by eying the glory ſet before them, and looking to that <hi>City that had foundations, whoſe builder and maker is God:</hi> And upon theſe and ſuch like conſiderations my ſoul was
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:93284:64"/> incouraged to follow Chriſt, reſolving in his ſtrength, I would do ſo in every of his Commands, he ſhould make known to me to be my duty to walk in; although by ſo doing I were a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and ſcorn; minding <hi>David's</hi> words,<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 71.7.</note> 
                  <hi>I am a wonder unto men: but thou art my ſtrong refuge.</hi> And thence I reaſoned, if God were my refuge I did not care, though I were a wonder unto men, in purſuit of my duty: &amp; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome further conſiderations, I ſaw Baptiſme more clear to be my duty; I being commanded,<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.12.</note> 
                  <hi>To follow thoſe who through Faith and patience inherit the promiſes:</hi> And this path of Baptiſm I find Chriſt and all his Diſciples walk'd in, and therefore in this I judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed I was to follow; being commanded to be a follower of them: I alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered,<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41.</note> 
                  <hi>Then they that gladly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the word were Baptized,</hi> &amp;c. I like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe conſidered Chriſts Commiſſion,<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Go teach all Nations, Baptizing them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Teaching them to obſerve all things that I Command you;</hi> Of which I find Baptiſme to be one: this ſtill cleared it up to my ſoul further as a duty; I alſo conſidered that the Laws of a King
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:93284:65"/> were to be obeyed by all his Subjects; and this I judged one of the Laws of Chriſt, and therefore to be obeyed by all his Subjects: I alſo weighed ſeveral other Scriptures about the nature, uſe, and ends of Baptiſme, particularly<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4, 5.</note> which did manifeſt to me, that Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme was a duty injoyned to all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers; they thereby manifeſting their conformity to Chriſt in his death, in order to their being raiſed up by him again, and brought forth in the Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of his Reſurrection unto newneſſe of life; all which I found much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging and ingaging my heart to that duty.</p>
               <p>This night alſo my ſleep was made very ſweet to me, through the Lord's goodneſſe: I waked often, and ſlept again, and ſtill found ſweet refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in my ſoul, ſeeing my ſelf very ſafe under the protection of Chriſt: I then endeavoured to ſleep again, minding what had been told me, that I ought to have compaſſion on my body; and my ſleep was comfortable to me: Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time I awaked, having theſe words given<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Zep.</hi> 3.17.</note> to me, <hi>He will reſt in his love:</hi> And theſe,<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>I am God, I change not,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:93284:65"/> and I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee:</hi> So that I was ſweetly compoſed, and inabled to rejoyce, under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of Chriſt, having thoſe words alſo brought to my mind,<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 31.21.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord hath ſhewed me his marvelous loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in a ſtrong City, and hath laid help upon one that is mighty:</hi> And that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Truſt in the Lord for ever, for in the Lord Jehovah is everlaſting ſtrength;</hi> in which my ſoul rejoyced greatly; as alſo in that word,<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai</hi> 40.11.</note> 
                  <hi>He ſhall gather the Lambs in his Arms, and carry them in his boſome, and gently lead thoſe that are with yong:</hi> From which the Lord gave me faith in my ſoul, that he was able to keep me, ſo as none ſhould be able to pluck me out of his hand; ſo that I was made to rejoyce in that unſpeakable ſafety that I had under his Protection. Another pretious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to me was,<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42.3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>A bruiſed Reed ſhall he not break, nor ſmoaking Flax ſhall he not quench, till he bring forth judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to victory: He ſhall not fail, nor be diſcouraged till he have ſet judgement in the Earth, and the Iſles ſhall wait for his Law:</hi> And hence I conſidered, that he was my Counſeller as well as my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:93284:66"/> and what a wonderful Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller he is! which I conſidered at large from<note n="(s)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Unto us a Child is born, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us a Son is given; the Government ſhall be upon his ſhoulders: and his name ſhall be called the wonderful Counſeller, the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Father, the Prince of peace; and of his Government and Kingdom there ſhall be no end:</hi> As likewiſe thoſe words came to my mind,<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22.</note> 
                  <hi>A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you, of your Brethren, like unto me him ſhall you hear in all things that he ſhall ſpeak:</hi> then was my heart lifted up, bleſſing the Lord for that plentious redemption, which he had let me ſee in Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that word,<note n="(u)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 103.</note> bleſſing him with whom there is ſuch plentiful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, to redeem <hi>Iſrael</hi> from all his iniquities, who Crowneth us with loving kindneſſe, &amp;c. and who hath bleſs'd us with all Spiritual bleſſings in Chriſt; having raiſed us, and made us ſit together in Heavenly places in Chriſt, that in the ages to come he might ſhew, what is the exceeding Riches of his grace, in his kindneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us in Chriſt, who hath delivered us from the Kingdom of darkneſſe, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:93284:66"/> hath tranſlated us into the Kingdom of his dear Son.</p>
               <p>I had alſo ſome pretious Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon that great deliverance I had by Jeſus Chriſt, from the dominion of ſin, Satan, and that greateſt bondage of all, to be in a natural condition; and that Chriſt had purchaſed perfect li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and freedom: ſo that I was now made free indeed, and made a parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the inheritance of the Saints in light. Yet after all this,<note place="margin">Her eighth Aſſault.</note> I was again ſorely aſſaulted, and tempted, to have low undervaluing thoughts of the grace of God, as if it were but a poor low thing; as alſo to blaſpheme againſt God: but the Lord did gratiouſly make me to cry to him for his aſſiſtance, to cauſe my ſoul to reſiſt the Devil, and loath and abominate his filthy ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, that ſo I might not diſhonour him by hearkning or conſenting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſeeing he had promiſed, <hi>He would never leave me, nor forſake me:</hi> That he would now make good his word, in which he had cauſed me to truſt; and by theſe (and many other promiſes) he inabled me to plead with him, who had ſaid, He would <hi>ſave to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:93284:67"/> and <hi>would tread down Satan under ſoot ſhortly; and that the Gates of Hell ſhould not prevail againſt me:</hi> All which I pleaded earneſtly with him, that he would ſtill cauſe me to experience the truth of this his-word, in which he had made my ſoul to hope: and at length (through his rich grace) I was inabled to ſay to his praiſe, That he was indeed a God that did never leave nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them that truſted in him; but did <hi>keep Covenant and mercy for ever,</hi> in that he had vanquiſhed the Devil, and cauſed me to relie on himſelf, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving me Faith in that pretious promiſe, <hi>That he would not break the bruiſed reed, till he had brought forth Judgement unto Victory:</hi> So that in the ſenſe of his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver failing nor forſaking me, my ſoul was made now greatly to rejoyce.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Further Aſſaults from Satan.</note>The ſecond day at evening, I had <hi>many firy darts, and filthy ſuggeſtions of Satan caſt into me:</hi> Which were excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding terrible unto me, and were born in with ſuch violence, as though the Devil ſtrove with all his might to cauſe me to caſt off my hopes that I had in God; urging me to <hi>blaſpheme God, and to think meanly and lowly of the grace of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:93284:67"/> God;</hi> Which cauſed in me great fears: but the Lord of his grace did not ſo leave me, as to ſuffer me to caſt off my confidence: But great was my fears, leſt I ſhould be left to diſhonour him by unbelief, after I had profeſs'd ſuch hope in him; and thereby alſo ſhould wound the peace of my own ſoul. I alſo conſidered, that if I ſhould conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in this condition, my life would be a burden to me, and I ſhould have cauſe to repent of the Profeſſion I had made of my hope in God; thinking what a great diſhonour this would be to his Name and Goſpel, and cauſe of ſtumbling to them who had heard me profeſſe my hope, cauſing them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour him alſo.</p>
               <p>But the Lord did help me (through his grace) to flie to him as my ſtrong re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, with ſecret breathings in my ſoul, that he would not deliver me up to the will of my Enemies: but he would now remember his good word, in which he had cauſed me to hope, that <hi>thoſe that came to him, he would in no wiſe caſt out, but ſave to the utmoſt, treading down Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan under the feet of ſuch:</hi> And I begg'd that he would open and inlarge my
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:93284:68"/> ſtrait heart, that my mouth might ſpeak of his goodneſſe, to the praiſe of his name. And the Lord did cauſe my ſoul again to experience his faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that he is a God that keeps Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and mercy for ever; and he did gratiouſly cauſe the Devil to flie, and gave great inlargement to my ſoul, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how greatly it was ſtraitened; and made me able to ſpeak to his praiſe; and did (by his good Spirit) bring theſe things to my remembrance, which I was not able to think of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and was again inabled to believe (through his grace) that he is a <hi>God that will keep truth for ever, and that no ſoul, that truſts in him, ſhould be deſolate:</hi> So that my ſoul was now made to ſay,<note n="(w)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 146.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed is the man that hath the God of Jacob for his help, whoſe hope is in the Lord his God, which made the Heavens, the Earth, the Seas, and all that is in them, and who keepeth truth for ever with them that fear him.</hi> Bleſſed be his name. I have been ſince pondering further the duty of Baptiſme aforeſaid, and had at ſome times much clearneſſe in it as a duty: yet doubts and queſtions have been caſt into my mind about it; and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:93284:68"/> thus I remained, debating it in my own thoughts, and conſulting Scriptures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, until the twentieth day of this eleventh Moneth at night; at which time I was ſet upon with terrible ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions about the lowneſſe and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, being much tempted to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe and ſlight it; which, when I had conſidered, cauſed great fears and fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in me, leſt I ſhould in my heart conſent to thoſe ſuggeſtions, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hinder my obedience to the Lord, as aforeſaid: And I was enabled to lift up my ſoul to the Lord for help at this time, againſt theſe ſuggeſtions and temptations, that I might reſiſt them; and the Lord inabled me now to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that no Command of Chriſt was to be accounted low, or ſmall Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring alſo I owed all ſervice and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Lord, both as I was his Creature, but more eſpecially as I was redeemed by him ſo marvellouſly as I have been, and with ſo great a price as the Blood of Jeſus. I alſo thought, what a ſad condition <hi>Adam</hi> brought all his Poſterity into, by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience at firſt, in but eating an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which was forbidden; as alſo
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:93284:69"/> what a poor Creature man was; and how unfit, unworthy, and unbecoming it was for him, to be diſputing with his Creator; who might do with all of us, as the Potter with his Clay, make or marre us at his pleaſure; and what a proud preſumptuous Creature I was, to ſuffer ſuch a thing to enter into my thoughts, that any of his Commands ſhould be diſputed, or thought by me to be low, or contemptible, which I looked on as an abominable evil in me; and deſired the Lord to look with an eye of Pardon and compaſſion upon me; and not to ſuffer me to hearken to the Devil's ſuggeſtions, to diſhonour him, but make me eſteem highly of all his Commands; deſiring he would (according to his promiſe) put his fear into my heart, that I might not depart from him; and that ſeeing he is <hi>able to ſave to the utmoſt,</hi> and had promiſed ſo to do, as alſo to <hi>tread down Satan under foot, and to work, and none ſhould let:</hi> All which he having given me experience of his making them good to my ſoul formerly, I now begg'd he would further ſtrengthen my Faith concerning them, as alſo in that good
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:93284:69"/> word of his, <hi>in keeping me by his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power through Faith unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> And now did I find the Lords gratious anſwer to my poor ſouls de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, in many of theſe things: as firſt, in upholding and keeping me againſt the Tempters ſuggeſtion, as I had deſired, that I was not overcome by them; though when I awaked this night, the Tempter met me again with his Aſſaults: but I was helpt to ſtrive againſt them, crying to the Lord for help to ſtand, &amp; ſtrength to overcome; and he did help and ſuccour me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and incouraged me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his word, and to call to mind the depths of diſtreſſes he had by his <hi>out-ſtretched Arm, and infinite love and pitty raiſed my ſoul out of:</hi> and he minded me, how he had ſupported me, when I was ready to ſink under the weight of my Iniquities, and wrath due to them; yet he then upheld me, and delivered me, and had ſaid he would not forſake me.</p>
               <p>Theſe conſiderations did ſupport and enable me ſtill to truſt in him, that had wrought ſo wonderfully, and appeared ſo eminently for my poor ſoul, as he
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:93284:70"/> had done; and I was now inabled to believe that good word,<note n="(x)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49.10.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſhall not hunger nor thirst, neither ſhall the heat of the Sun ſmite them: for he that hath mercy on them ſhall lead them, even by the ſprings of Waters ſhall he guide them:</hi> As alſo that,<note n="(y)" place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 7.38.</note> 
                  <hi>He that believeth on me, the Scripture hath ſaid, out of his belly ſhall flow Rivers of living waters:</hi> Theſe (with many more promiſes) were now given in, fully anſwering to all my wants, and removing my fears: I was alſo inabled <hi>to judge him faithful that had promiſed,</hi> and ſo to look upon his promiſes as ſo many love-tokens from him, in the way of his free grace to my ſoul, through Chriſt my Redeemer: and ſeeing Baptiſm now (upon all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations aforeſaid) my duty, to which again was added afreſh this Scripture,<note n="(z)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Therefore we are buried with him by Baptiſm into death,</hi> &amp;c. And my ſoul laid under the Power of the truth in it, that as I did expect advantage by the Lord Chriſt his death and Reſurrection to my poor ſoul, ſo I ought by my viſible obedience to this his Command, to declare my putting him on, and my being planted in the likeneſſe of his
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:93284:70"/> death, being buried with him by Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm into death; and alſo my being raiſed with and by him, and the Power of his Reſurrection, unto newneſſe of life; and my reſolving (in his ſtrength) to walk accordingly: all which ends Baptiſm, (according to this Scripture) I judged lively held forth; I was upon the whole inabled to come to reſolve, (through grace) to yield obedience thereunto, as unto a Command of Chriſt my Lord, expecting his aſſiſtance and bleſſing therein: According to his word,<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 14.21.</note> 
                  <hi>He that hath my Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and keepeth them, he it is that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth me; and he that loveth me, ſhall be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of my Father; and I will love him, and will manifeſt my ſelf unto him:</hi> As alſo that word,<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 64.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou meeteſt him that rejoyceth, and worketh Righteouſneſs, thoſe that remember thee in thy wayes.</hi> In the Faith of which promiſes, and fear of the name of the Lord, I intend (through his gratious aſſiſtance) to yeeld obedience accordingly in that and all his Commandments; the love of Chriſt being of a conſtraining nature to my ſoul, by which I have been cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to conſider what he hath done for
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:93284:71"/> me, in perfecting the work of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and alſo to think how little I am called to do or ſuffer for him, who hath done ſo much for my ſake,<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.5.</note> 
                  <hi>He being wounded for our tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and bruiſed for our Iniquities, the chaſtiſements of our peace being on him, by whoſe ſtripes we are healed:</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Who being in the Forme of God, thought it no robbery to be equal with God, yet made he himſelf of no Reputation, but humbled himſelf, and became obedient to death, even to the death of the Croſſe for our ſakes:</hi> Theſe conſiderations are of a Conſtraining nature to my ſoul, to obey him in all things.</p>
               <p>I alſo conſidered what I ſhould have undergone to Eternity, had it not been for what he hath done and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to deliver me from wrath to come; I alſo thought how little all the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this world are to thoſe I ſhould have under-gone, had not he Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me from thoſe Eternal miſeries, which indeed makes all the afflictions of this preſent life ſeem little and light to me, when I ſeriouſly think of them: According to that,<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18.</note> 
                  <hi>For I rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon the ſufferings of this preſent time are not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:93284:71"/> worthy to be compared with the glory that ſhall be revealed in us;</hi> and that,<note n="(f)" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>our light affliction that is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding, and Eternal weight of glory, while we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen: for the things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are Eternal;</hi> and that,<note n="(g)" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14.</note> 
                  <hi>the love of Christ conſtrains us, becauſe we thus judge, that if Christ died for all, then were all dead, that they which live ſhould not live unto themſelves, but unto him which died for them, and roſe again:</hi> And that,<note n="(h)" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20.</note> 
                  <hi>for you are bought with a price, therefore glorify God, both in your ſouls and bodies, which are his; and ought to be offered up as a living ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Holy and acceptable unto him, which is but our reaſonable ſervice, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the will of him who hath of his own will begotten us unto a lively Faith in Christ Jeſus, unto whom be glory in the Churches (by Christ Jeſus) thorowout all Ages, World without end, AMEN.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="abstract">
            <pb facs="tcp:93284:72"/>
            <head>An abſtract of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal parts of the fore-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Narrative, which the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will find to be in ſubſtance as followeth; though by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the mixture and variety of the matter, it cannot be ſo diſtinctly compoſed, as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it might be.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>I. A</hi> Particular Relation of her diſtreſſed eſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for fourteen years time, wherein ſhe was exerciſed with various tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, concluding herſelf guilty of the unpardonable ſin, and ſo a ſubject of the wrath of God; <hi>Whch ſhe day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expected to be poured down upon her, and was hopeleſſe of any deliverance, notwithſtanding the frequent means uſed by many for her relief, both by fervent Prayers for her, and Faithful endeavours by Chriſtian advice and counſel to her; from</hi> Pag. <hi>1.</hi> to Pag. <hi>19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>II.</hi> A Particular diſcovery of the
<pb facs="tcp:93284:72"/> Lords manner of working on her heart by his word and Spirit, convincing her of her ſinful ſtate, and helping her to look unto Christ alone for Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; notwithſtanding many fears mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with her hopes: From Pag. <hi>19.</hi> to Pag. <hi>31.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>III.</hi> A diſcovery of ſeveral Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults from the Tempter, and gratious ſupplies of ſtrength from the Lord, by which ſhe was helped to reſist them, and to flie unto him for refuge: From Pag. <hi>31.</hi> to Pag. <hi>40.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>IV.</hi> Several pretious promiſes, and ſeaſonable words, brought in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>werfully to her ſoul, for her ſupport and ſuccour under ſeveral Aſſaults: From Pag. <hi>40.</hi> to Pag. <hi>56.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>V.</hi> She is helped to conſider what ſhe ſhall render unto the Lord for all his benefits and ſpecial deliverances he hath wrought for her, and is helped to reſolve in his ſtrength, to give up her ſelf as a living and acceptable ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice unto his ſervice: From Pag. <hi>56.</hi> to the end.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table">
            <pb facs="tcp:93284:73"/>
            <head>A TABLE, Containing ſeveral Texts of Scripture that were variouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, according to her ſtate and condition; as the Reader may perceive, by comparing them with the ſeveral places to which this Table directs.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I. Scriptures made uſe of to increaſe terror in her diſtreſſed eſtate.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>HEb.</hi> 10.27, 29. <hi>Pag.</hi> 4</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 65.5. <hi>Pag.</hi> 5</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.31. <hi>Pag.</hi> 6</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5, 6. <hi>Pag.</hi> 8</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 57.20, 21. <hi>Pag.</hi> 11</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.26. <hi>Pag.</hi> 12</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.11. <hi>Pag.</hi> 13</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Joel</hi> 2.31. <hi>Pag.</hi> 14</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>II. Scriptures made uſe of to convince her of her ſinful and ſad eſtate.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>COl.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Pag</hi> 19</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 50.23. <hi>Pag.</hi> 20</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:93284:73"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.155. <hi>Pag.</hi> 21</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 50.16. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>III. Scriptures made uſe of to incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage her to wait upon the Lord in the uſe of means, to truſt in him, and to follow him fully.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>HEſter</hi> 4, 16. <hi>Pag.</hi> 23</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Kings</hi> 7.4. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John</hi> 6.37. <hi>Pag.</hi> 30</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.13. <hi>Pag.</hi> 31</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 63.8. <hi>Pag.</hi> 34</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Pag.</hi> 35</item>
                  <item>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Pag.</hi> 36</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Pag.</hi> 38</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Pag.</hi> 40</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>IV. Several choice promiſes, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious words brought powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to her ſoul, for her ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port &amp; engaging to duty.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>ISai.</hi> 45.17, 24, 25. <hi>Pag.</hi> 40</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 84.11. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John</hi> 7.17. <hi>Pag.</hi> 41</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:93284:74"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 32.8. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6.3. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.20. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 36.8. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 25.6. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Pag.</hi> 45</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>1 <hi>John</hi> 1.9. <hi>Pag.</hi> 49.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 68.18. <hi>Pag.</hi> 50</item>
                  <item>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55, 56, 57. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Titus</hi> 3.4, 5. <hi>Pag.</hi> 51</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 16.6. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 34.22. <hi>Pag.</hi> 52</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 33.16, 17. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.12. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.30. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.29. <hi>Pag.</hi> 53</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John</hi> 14.27. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John</hi> 14.19. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Job</hi> 5.19. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.11. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 27.3. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 41.17. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55.3. <hi>Pag.</hi> 54</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Malach.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Pag.</hi> 60</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 31.21. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 61</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.3. <hi>Pag Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 40.11. <hi>Pag Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:93284:74"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42.3, 4. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Pag.</hi> 62</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 103.3. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Pag.</hi> 55</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Pag.</hi> 73</item>
                  <item>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>V. Scriptures convincing and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming her in the duty of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and even conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning her thereunto.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>HEb.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Pag.</hi> 59</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4, 5. <hi>Pag.</hi> 60</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John</hi> 14.21. <hi>Pag.</hi> 71</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 64 5. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.5. <hi>Pag.</hi> 72</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7, 8. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VI. Scriptures ſupporting her in the thoughts of ſufferings.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>PHil</hi> 1.29. <hi>Pag.</hi> 57</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.37. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marke</hi> 10.29. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:93284:75"/>
                  <item>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17, 18. <hi>Pag.</hi> 58</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 71.7. <hi>Pag.</hi> 59</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rom</hi> 8.18. <hi>Pag.</hi> 72</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VII. Scriptures by which ſhe was relieved againſt her fears, under ſeveral Aſſaults: And had her hopes of freſh ſupplies from the Lord increaſed.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>HEb.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Pag.</hi> 55</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20. <hi>Pag.</hi> 65</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John</hi> 6.37. <hi>Pag.</hi> 30</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> 146.5. <hi>Pag.</hi> 66</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49.10. <hi>Pag.</hi> 70</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John</hi> 7.38. <hi>Pag. Idem.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <p>The Reader is deſired to take notice, that ſome of the Texts in this Table are not mentioned in the Margent; onely the words expreſſed in the Page, which being but ſhort, may ſoon be diſcerned.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SEveral Faults having eſcaped the Preſſe; I have pointed out the Chief, which thou art deſired to take notice of. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt Epiſtle, Page <hi>11.</hi> Line <hi>9.</hi> read <hi>Iſai. 59.</hi> In the Book, p. <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> for <hi>irrecoverable</hi> re. <hi>irrevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable.</hi> p. <hi>4.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> r. <hi>remained.</hi> p. <hi>5.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> r. <hi>made it.</hi> and l. <hi>4.</hi> re. <hi>mind.</hi> p. <hi>7.</hi> l. <hi>21.</hi> re. <hi>hatred.</hi> p. <hi>22.</hi> Margent, re. <hi>2 Kings 7.4.</hi> pag. <hi>30.</hi> Margent, read <hi>John 6.37.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93284:75"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
